germayne: Hello, hello, can everyone hear me?
germayne: Hi, hi, good evening.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: I don't…
germayne: Hey, hi, hi, Jaga.
germayne: Okay, everybody, are you guys ready? I know it's a… it's a cold weather.
germayne: Okay… Okay, I think we can begin.
germayne: Okay, so for… for the last… for the last week of Module 3, how we are going to end off Module 3 this week is that we are going to focus specifically on the NLP domain. So essentially, today we are going to talk
germayne: mostly from a data perspective, if you are thinking in terms of unstructured data, we will be talking about text. Tax data.
germayne: Okay? So, from the… if you think across the different… different…
germayne: each of the different weeks. We have talked about your tabular data, we have gone on to see things like your time series sequential data.
germayne: we have seen image data last week, and today, what we are going to finish off would be, we'll be talking about NLP, which is text data. So.
germayne: We're going to think about this in two parts.
germayne: The first part today is really more of an introduction to NLP.
germayne: So, it's about the processing of the data, it's also about certain ways of representing these text data.
germayne: And it's kind of… You know, a precursor to a lot of the modern
germayne: State-of-the-art mechanism that is actually used to understand
germayne: linguistic or text data, right? And I think on Saturday, you guys sort of seen a bit about the… the REG system. So that is just one application of using large language model, but for… for today, we are going to start off with the basic foundation of
germayne: You know, what… do you pros… how do you actually process text data? How is it represented?
germayne: And we're going to walk slowly from some of the traditional methodology that's used. And on Thursday, we will then talk about the application of deep learning back into NLP.
germayne: Of course, we are not going to jump straight into the latest state of the art, but on… on today, we will start with the foundation, and then you will get a glimpse. Again, it's a… again, NLP itself is, like, a different topic.
germayne: Right? You'll get a glimpse of the basic foundation, and with that, you are free to explore beyond the class if you feel that NLP is something that you want to focus on. So obviously, you can see that all this requires a lot of domain.
germayne: Text data, sorry.
germayne: image data itself is also a separate domain, right? So, I think after this, you guys can start… you guys will basically have the foundation to…
germayne: You know, specialize in whatever domain that you are interested in, or… You know, if your work
germayne: It has some relevance to it.
germayne: Okay, so you can see we are really towards the end, and this is the last week with you guys. Of course, it's not the end of your journey yet, it's just the end of the journey with me.
germayne: For now.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so really, we are going to do, like, a four portion. We'll really understand text processing, we'll talk a bit about text representation, we will revisit vector space, essentially
germayne: you know, if you guys were thinking about these from Saturday, you know, when we think about the retrieval problem that we'll mention, actually this is going to be relevant again, and we will talk about word embeddings.
germayne: And lastly, we will end off with text classification from a traditional standpoint.
germayne: Okay, and you will see that in your notebook today.
germayne: Okay, so…
germayne: Essentially, NLP is really the, you know, the full acronym for NLP is Natural Language Processing, so it's really about, you know, how do we actually reason about the linguistic perspective
germayne: Right? And essentially, this is the backbone of…
germayne: the latest advancements and application that we have seen today, right? But actually, the thing about NLP is that it has existed way long ago, right? It is not… you know, NLP has been studied for a long time.
germayne: I have been doing NLP since 2016, I think, but I believe even before that, NLP has existed.
germayne: Of course, along the way, because of the algorithms, because of the… again, same story as computer vision, because of, like, the advancement of the hardware, right? Essentially, all these sort of, like, translate into a different application.
germayne: But this has already been done very long ago using traditional machine learning.
germayne: So you can see, email filtering, anything that has to do with text data, right? Summarization, translation, this actually all involves using NLP. I believe you guys should remember that even back then, you know, you have Google Translate, right? Basically, you're doing translation between different languages.
germayne: these actually are all applications of NLP, right? Sentiment analysis, you know, given a text or paragraph, you know, is the sentiment positive or not? So all of these can be done using traditional machine learning.
germayne: Okay? So nothing has… I think the application layer has, of course, evolved.
germayne: Right? Becomes more powerful.
germayne: But all of this has already been done in the past.
germayne: Alright, so we're going to revisit some of these basic foundations.
germayne: Okay, so, you know, the idea here is that
germayne: all of these are, you know, used in different, different areas. So you can see here, we have, you know, search engine queries.
germayne: you know, if you remember, Google actually has search engine, right? If you type in, like, the words, how do we actually retrieve documentation? So these are actually part of the application of NLP. Chatbot is also one of them. You know, summarization of all your documents, all of these are the
germayne: Some of the basic applications of using text data.
germayne: Okay, so I think I will leave this to you guys, but essentially, the transformation of the text data in terms of the application was that people started with statistical model, RNN and LSTM, we will talk about this.
germayne: on Thursday. So essentially, it's one of the architecture of
germayne: neural network, right? So essentially, we call it the recurring neural network and the long, short-term memory architecture. Obviously, these are already outdated today because of Transformer, right? But…
germayne: I think it's still… it's still applicable to know it.
germayne: Okay? And you will see what's the difference with, you know, how can… how can such specific architecture, similar to computer vision, why is it that it made sense for text data?
germayne: Of course, then you have the language modeling, you have things like the word embedings, which is, like, kind of the state of the art, to some extent, in terms of embedings, right? And then, of course, that powers Google Translate. Word2Vec is also, you know, by now, it's also sort of outdated.
germayne: Right? Then, encoder-decoder, again, it's a very generic term, but back then, encoder-decoder, people usually associate that to this thing called sequence-to-sequence, usually used for translation tasks. But encoder-decoder, again, is just a generic term.
germayne: From a neural network perspective, right?
germayne: I mentioned that if you were to project and input data to a high dimension, it's usually called encoding, and decoding is usually, you know, taking in these high representation output and using them for a specific task.
germayne: So that's a typical term for encoder-decoder. Of course, attention was… actually, I'm not even sure, I don't… okay, I think attention came out very long ago, but I remember the first
germayne: model that gained popularity, the BERT model. Actually, I think it was…
germayne: you know, I think early 2017, I believe, right? And then, of course, today we have the pre-trained model, and then…
germayne: I think a couple of years back, GPT 3.5, I think, was the first one that
germayne: Got a big boom.
germayne: Right? But it has existed for quite some time, right? I think pre-GPT 3.5, GPT3, GPT 2.5, I think those are open source.
germayne: Okay? So, you know, I'm sure some of you already know this, this is, like, part of everybody's life now, but the interesting thing is that all this miracle actually came from NLP.
germayne: Okay, I think, enough about these, I think we will give certain examples.
germayne: Okay, so just like what I mentioned, NLP is really…
germayne: the application of using text data. So, essentially, you're thinking about unstructured data, right? Again, from a… from a computer perspective, you need to understand that it doesn't understand language like human, right? When you think… when you look… when you see, say, text… textural data, right, it doesn't have this level of understanding. So.
germayne: historically, people have always been thinking about how do you reason about this text data from a computer perspective? You saw that even for images, right, there are traditional computer vision techniques in order to break down the image itself, right? Because
germayne: how do we actually have some kind of reasoning on these kind of unstructured data, right? And all this actually translated to things like your text classification. Essentially, people do a lot of feature engineering in the past.
germayne: Right? And then people put it into the… all the traditional machine learning model that you have seen. Of course, that is no longer applicable because of all the pre-trained models that are really, really good.
germayne: Machine translation back then, sequence-to-sequence, deep learning, LSTM models was really good at it, right? And then, of course, Google Translate was powered by such machine translation. Sentiment analysis is very, very common. Basically, the task here is a classification task.
germayne: Given a text or sentence, how do you predict whether it's a positive or negative sentiment? So, essentially, it's a classification task.
germayne: Chatbot, obviously today, large language model has completely changed chatbot, but I think in the past, chatbot is a very complex application. I'm pretty sure you guys know that Siri and Alexa existed way before large language model.
germayne: Right? I'm sure you guys know about that. I believe I was playing with it in, what, 2016, 2015? I don't think large language models was available back then.
germayne: Right, so people broke it down, you know, into understanding the intent. Because end of the day, when you're communicating, there's an intent, right? It's not just a word. You know, there's some intention behind. So people were thinking about, oh, you know, is there a way to predict what's the intent of this sentence and stuff?
germayne: And then, of course, there's summarization, information extraction, topic modeling, speech recognition, Q&A, etc, etc. So you can see NLP is
germayne: Obviously, because of large language model now, it is the most talked about, Let's talk about application.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Yeah, okay, so also a lot of things is that you'll start to see
germayne: you know, for very basic NLP,
germayne: algorithms, you will start to see that we actually don't talk about semantics. Okay, so I want to introduce, if this is the first time that you are thinking about semantics, right, is that, you know, the idea about your text data is that it's not always just looking at the keywords.
germayne: What I mean by that is, let's say, for example, when you talk about, like, things like healthy foods, right? You know, you can see this example here. Organic carrots and kale. Obviously, there's nothing to do with healthy food.
germayne: Right?
germayne: you can see something like this shady health gadget. So, what it's trying to illustrate here is that for, you know, for some of the old school algorithms, a lot of them looks at the matching of the text.
germayne: Right, so if there's something that is health, you want to look for, you know, there's a match with healthy, health, healthcare, whatever, right? Food, you look for, like, anything that has the word food. But then I want to ask you guys, is this…
germayne: Is this generally true? That text matching is the only important way to identify words that are similar?
germayne: must the sentence and the characters be the same? Not really, right?
germayne: You guys… are you guys able to follow? So, essentially, what you want to think about is what we call semantics. So, essentially, there's a meaning behind a word, but semantically, it means the same.
germayne: Right? For example, if you think about fast food, you would think you'll associate it with things like Burger King and McDonald's, right? But from a keyword perspective, they are… they are not exactly matching.
germayne: Now, before I go on, I just want to ask you guys from an intuition standpoint. Do you guys think that keyword matching is useless?
germayne: So, if, let's say, we are saying that semantics is very important, that we want to understand the deeper meaning behind each of the words, the hidden meaning, the semantics meaning, does that mean that exact keyword matching is useless? Is this statement true?
germayne: Okay, so I see a lot of people saying no, right? Why? I want to get some… some… some intuition. Why… why do you guys feel that? Oh, actually, keyword matching is important. Why?
germayne: Can't I just do semantics for all?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: He will search his bus.
germayne: Oh, okay.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: It's faster, like, in a sense, you don't need to look for the semantics behind the words, right?
germayne: Okay, but, okay, I think, I think, valid point, valid point, okay? So, so basically, Philip's point is simple, simple and fast. What else? Is simple and fast the only reason?
germayne: So, Philip, if that is the case, the question back to you is that if, let's say, that semantics search can be equally fast than lexical, so we call it lexical, right? Then doesn't mean that lexical search is redundant?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Blend it all.
germayne: Okay, okay, interesting. Anybody else? Any answer?
germayne: Any example, any example in real life where you feel that semantic search… sorry, lexical, which is a keyword matching, is still important?
germayne: Anyone, anyone got any idea?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Oh, please go… clinical names are… are things that cannot be… you cannot find out semantic. It's like certain…
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Certain words are used in certain industries that you cannot, frame it in another way, then, keyword search is… is…
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: It's universal, like, you will definitely get that answer that you were looking for already.
germayne: Hmm,
germayne: So basically, okay, so basically, the long story short is that there are some specific use cases, okay? I'll give you guys a very simple intuition.
germayne: So, if you guys remember things like your poster code, Things like your block number.
germayne: 100C, 100B. Those are keyword match, right? There's no way you can match by semantics.
germayne: So, so you guys, you guys get the idea that actually keyword match is still important. Okay, so nobody here is saying that, oh, you know, just because we can do semantics, we are throwing away lexical, okay?
germayne: Okay, so I think with that, right, so what we are going to start today is really just talk about some of the basic tax preprocessing. So, you have seen that, you know, in a lot of your numerical data, you know, you will basically compute the statistics, you will check whether there's null values, you know, you'll check whether there's outliers.
germayne: So I think same thing for text processing. So text processing, from a basic foundation standpoint, is also thinking about how can you, you know, clean the text data. Because the idea here is that, you know, when you want to process the text data, or you want to use it for any downstream algorithm.
germayne: maybe you might need to remove the noise from the data itself, right? So you shouldn't be just using the raw, the text data. So today, what we will see is that
germayne: You know, some of the basic foundations would be, you know, we'll think… we'll explain that later, but the idea here is that, you know, there are things about, like, you know, your typo, formatting is wrong, things like certain keywords that, you know, maybe the algorithm might not understand, stop words, you know, we'll see later, things that are not very useful.
germayne: So a lot of this.
germayne: Again, boils down to some of the thought process in cleaning the data from a preprocessing manner, but this is applied more on the text data.
germayne: Okay, so another, another, another term you will see here is this item, this idea that is known as a token, right? Essentially, tokenizing.
germayne: So, of course, there are many different tokenizing mechanisms used today, but from a very simplistic standpoint, there are actually very basic ways of thinking of splitting your text data into smaller subunits, right? So the reason for doing this is, end of the day, we need to think about this
germayne: text data has some form of fixed vocabulary, right? So, very, very simple, let's say, out of the box.
germayne: Right? A very simple way of, let's say, splitting a paragraph or a sentence is just to split by the white space. So essentially, now each of your vocabulary will just be all of the unique words, right? So if, let's say, in this example, your sentence is, I love cats, then essentially you can think of the unique vocabulary would be, I love, and cats.
germayne: Okay? And then you can also split by characters, right? Basically, you split each of the individual… so high becomes H and I, and then, of course, you can split into sentences from paragraph.
germayne: And obviously, these are just 3 simple examples. In reality, there are many tokenization mechanisms that people have created, right? And the intuition here is that
germayne: Essentially, even for some of the large language models that you are using, they have some form of vocab, right? Some form of vocabulary, where they are actually able to split the input data into certain mechanisms for the tokenization mechanism.
germayne: Right? And each model, they have… they might have their own closed-source mechanism or open source mechanism to do the tokenization.
germayne: So essentially, the takeaway here is that people don't process data with the entire input, right? If you have a storybook, you have a textbook, you do not process the data raw, right? You don't put in the whole chunk of text. Essentially, you have to split them up into its own individual tokens, and then, you know, we would then process this data.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So here is the simple thing of, like, tokenization. You will see some basic tokenization later in the notebook.
germayne: Okay, this is also another… another common preprocessing method. It's basically what we call stemming. So you can see stamming, essentially, is one way of transforming a lot of these data, which has, essentially, you know, we just want to convert them to their common form. And here you can see in this example, you have things like running.
germayne: flies, happiness. Essentially, what you want to do is, you realize that on the right-hand side, there are actually many forms of the language, but what you want is that stemming actually, essentially, find a common
germayne: Word, the common word, and converting them into the common form.
germayne: And the idea here is, you want to think about this, is you want… you might also want to reduce the variation of these words, because they might mean similar things, right? And you might want to keep the vocabulary smaller.
germayne: Right? Same thing for studying, study, study, this, essentially, there's a… there's the same meaning behind. But one thing you notice is that stemming actually sort of removed the correct
germayne: word, right? And this is just one mechanism. Of course, it's a very simple mechanism, where we can really just convert each of these words that has multiple forms into its most common
germayne: word, right? The common corrector.
germayne: Okay, so you can see the result… the note here is that the resulting stem might not be a real word, and it is really just a rule-based processing mechanism, and might not be linguistically correct.
germayne: Then, of course, there's also another form of processing called dilemmatization. So, as opposed to stemming.
germayne: rather than just cut away and find the common correctors, what you essentially do is that you want to use a linguistic approach in order to revert the word to its common form. So running…
germayne: will become run, right? Better will just become good, studies will become study, and worse will become B, okay? So you can see, as compared to stemming.
germayne: It's a more natural approach to converting each of the words into its base form.
germayne: Okay? And, of course, it has its own vocabulary and mechanism, and…
germayne: The idea here is that lemmatization actually allows us to preprocess the data to convert all of this into its base common form. And again, the result is that it will actually reduce the vocabulary size for some of these basic methods that we'll be talking about.
germayne: Then the… another thing to talk about, as we mentioned, is this concept of top stop words. Has you guys… as you guys would understand.
germayne: if you were to, you know, look into some kind of paragraphs, there will be a lot of stop words that might not be important. So things like, you can see some of the example, the, is, in, at, which, all of these, you know.
germayne: enrich the context of the sentences, but might not have meaning. So later on, for some of the algorithm, right, some of the traditional algorithm, you will see that actually we might want to remove them.
germayne: Right? Again, we want to restrict the overall vocabulary size, and we know that it does not really matter, you know, because of the stop work. Like, we can just basically process by removing them.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: And of course, we'll learn certain mechanisms to do it either heuristically or using the data. And then you can see some example here is the cat is on the mat, right?
germayne: The idea here is the is really not very important. You can just remove it, doesn't really serve any meaning, right? Is also, so something like that. So essentially, if you were to remove the stop words, then you'll arrive at CAPMAT.
germayne: Okay? So what's the reason for this? It's because you will see later on, for some of the basic algorithms, the dimension is defined by the vocabulary size.
germayne: Okay? So, in order to handle this data, you do not want to handle all of these stop words, so usually they are being removed.
germayne: Okay? So you really want to focus on what is meaningful, essentially the nouns, the verbs, and some of the adjectives, right?
germayne: But of course, it's difficult to know what to remove.
germayne: Right? And sometimes things like this would affect the meaning. Okay? So in practice, it's difficult, might be depending on your domain, but you will see later there are also mechanisms to sort of, you know, making use of the data of the documents that we are processing to help us determine what are the stock words.
germayne: Okay, so I think we went through, like, a lot of, like, very, very…
germayne: basic concepts, but I'll stop here first. I'll give a pause.
germayne: Anybody has any last questions before I continue?
germayne: Okay, so these are still fairly basic, right? So we'll go through them in detail later.
germayne: Okay, so within NLP itself, there's actually a lot of…
germayne: So, at a very high level, we learn about things like your classification and regression. But within the NLP domain, there's actually a lot more further breakdown, you know, we break down a lot of these.
germayne: tasks into very different, specific tasks. And one of the… one of the tasks within the NLP is actually what is known as the part of speech tagging.
germayne: So essentially, the idea here is that you have a sentence, right? You might want to predict what are the texts, you know, whether if each of the sentences is a pronoun, it's a verb.
germayne: Essentially, right? So you can see this. So this is actually what people call the part of speech. Again, this is a very specific use case.
germayne: But where this is actually going to is that there's actually a more general task called the name-entity Recognition.
germayne: So basically what we call the NUR task. So NUR…
germayne: from the NLP perspective, it's actually a classification task, right? And the idea here is that, given a sentence, you might actually want to classify certain tagging based on the keywords. So in this example here, you can see that
germayne: the… the… we have certain sentences here, and each of these sentences, we are basically trying to predict which one is a person, which one is a company, so you can see organization. So, essentially, it's… it's a… it's a…
germayne: I would say this is like a…
germayne: Classification tasks, essentially, for each of the… each of the…
germayne: input… input tags. Essentially, what we are trying to predict is what exactly is the name-entity recognition. So essentially… and depending on your problem statement, you can define your own
germayne: Text.
germayne: Right?
germayne: So, an example, for example, one use case that we use, name-entity Recognition, right, is that we, you know, maybe if, let's say, you want to extract out certain information based on the documents, you might want to find out, like, okay, maybe I want to do certain processing, I want to find out how many times a certain person is mentioned. One way is to actually formulate this as a name entity recognition task.
germayne: So, essentially, for each
germayne: token, you will make a prediction, right, a multi-classification problem. If, let's say, you define that each
germayne: token can only be classified as one entity, then essentially you can make a prediction for each of the tokens, and you'll be able to identify whether if certain things are being mentioned. And this is actually very useful if you want to make certain extraction out of the text.
germayne: input.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: All good? So, part of Stitch, I think, is a very specific task, but the… the exact
germayne: problem formulation here is the name-entity Recognition. So you will see that there are certain formulations for NLP use case where it's built in order to perform NER classification.
germayne: Okay, so one of the… one of the use cases that people tend to use in, let's say, ride-hailing, right? Again, this is open, so I'm not sharing anything… I'm not sharing anything that is a secret. So what people do is that, actually, you can also use some of the speech data… some of the text data that we have. You can actually try to identify certain categories.
germayne: in order to extract them out. So, for example, you guys might say that something like, oh, you know, can you pick me up at 7-Eleven? And basically what we can do is, if we do the inference on your text data, we can actually basically identify certain locations that's mentioned in your chats.
germayne: Okay, so there are obviously many applications of NER here.
germayne: Okay? All clear?
germayne: Any question?
germayne: How to decide which word or sentence to extract?
germayne: What do you mean? Sorry, I'm trying to understand the question. What do you mean by what do you… what… how do you decide what word or sentence to extract?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, just on you.
germayne: Beautiful.
Chieh Cheng Lai: You mentioned… you mentioned that this one is useful for the
Chieh Cheng Lai: words or sentences for extraction, but I just don't understand, is the…
Chieh Cheng Lai: We use name entity as a basics rule.
Chieh Cheng Lai: And see the commonality, and then to extract the… extract the words, like a token.
germayne: Yeah, so the… okay, so I think your question is…
germayne: how do we actually use NER, is it? Is that the question?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yes, correct.
germayne: Okay, so… okay, so I'll repeat again, so, I think it depends on your use case. So, for example, for example, it could be that you might be… you might be… okay, I'll give you another example. So, for example, you guys… does everybody know what is PII data?
germayne: Anybody knows what PII is?
germayne: Basically, yeah, your personal identification.
germayne: Right? Like, basically, some of your full name, things like your NRAC, etc.
germayne: So let's say, suppose, right, you want to build a system, and you are very interested to remove PII data.
germayne: If… if… let's say, traditionally, you have a… you have a text, let's say you have a… you have, like, some kind of…
germayne: Sentences in the chat logs that people are chatting.
germayne: It's not possible to write a heuristic rule to detect
germayne: where the PII data is, right?
germayne: can follow. If I were to manually decide that, okay, I'm just going to write a rule base, maybe it's possible, but then there's going to be, like, a lot of different variation, and your rule-based system might miss out. So one way to formulate it is, you do a NER,
germayne: classification. So essentially, for every word, you make a prediction whether if
germayne: what is exactly mentioned? Is it, like, some PII? Is it some vulgar, vulgarities, etc?
germayne: So you can make that prediction, and then you can, once you classify already, you can just remove, right? If you know where it is.
germayne: Does that… does that make sense?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, that's correct. Yeah, this makes sense. So…
Chieh Cheng Lai: So, in this case, we need to, do we need to defy the name entity? Because just now you've mentioned.
germayne: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, good question, good question. Yes, you need to define it, and you need a label date, you need a… you need to have a labored data of the entire entity to train the model, yes.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay, I understand, thank you.
germayne: So you get to define, because end of the day, end of the day.
germayne: let's say if you're using a neural network to do name-entity recognition, you're making… you're essentially just making a multi-classification. So, essentially, what you're doing here is you're just trying to predict for each token.
germayne: Again, in this example, let's suppose the token is the very basic tokenization of splitting by
germayne: white space, so you can imagine these are all tokens, right? Again, I'm just simplifying this example.
germayne: Right, so each of the, each of the space, and then each of the words is a… is a, is a token.
germayne: So what will happen is when you use a neural network, you can predict
germayne: what is this? What is this? What is this? What is this? So essentially, you can make a prediction for everything, and obviously, there are some labels that will be… you won't really care, but there will be some that you care, right, depending on the NER. And you are free to define whatever that you want to predict.
germayne: It's just a… it's just a multi-classification. You get to… you get to define what is the… what is the target label that you are interested in.
germayne: Okay, does that, does that, does that make sense?
germayne: So it's not like, oh, you are forced to do only persons, you can do anything you want. But the… the… has…
germayne: Of course, the caveat here is just like any other algorithm, you need to have the labored data, so somebody needs to label this.
germayne: Make sense?
germayne: Can everybody follow? All good?
germayne: Any other thing? Shall I move?
Edwin Yap: Jamin, there's a question from Philip.
germayne: payload.
Edwin Yap: Can we…
germayne: use NERR for document reduction?
germayne: Where target labours are named… yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, that can be… that can be one use case, yes, of course.
germayne: Of course.
germayne: It's up… okay, I think by now, right, you guys can see that there's no hard and fast rule of building a system. And that is the… that is where the… I think you guys… you guys, you guys heard me say this many times, right?
germayne: Now, right, you get to learn about all the different mechanisms, but it's up to you to how to solve the problem.
germayne: Correct? So it could be that, in this case, you guys, like, want to, oh, I want to detect PII data.
germayne: You know, nobody is saying that you have to do NERR to do that, but I'm just saying that if you look about this from a problem formulation standpoint.
germayne: The part of speech tagging, right, was built there because people just want to predict where's the noun, where's the verb, where's the adjective, agree?
germayne: If you can predict which is the null, which is the verb, which is the adjective.
germayne: What makes you think I can't predict which is the person, which is the company, which is the date? But then, does it mean that I can only predict person, CO, and date? No, right?
germayne: I just gave an example that you can predict whether there's valgravities, whether there's PII, whether there are things that are important. So you can do whatever you want, as long as somebody actually labored the data, and this is a key point of problem formulation.
germayne: Okay, so back to your answer, hopefully I answered your question right, Philip.
germayne: Right?
germayne: So yes, as long as it's a multi-classification, you have the labor data, you can predict anything that you want.
germayne: Okay Okay, so actually we reached the first part.
germayne: All good so far.
germayne: Okay, all good, right? Okay, so I'll hand over to Sun to take part 1 first, then we will come back for part two and part 3.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Yep.
Soon | NTU: Angie me.
Soon | NTU: Now, for the first part, can y'all see my screen? Can I?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: You haven't share your screen.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, yeah, okay.
Soon | NTU: Just click share.
Soon | NTU: Now, the first part of the, notebook, right, you can… Go to this section…
Soon | NTU: Cargie, okay, where are we?
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: tokenization Kia.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, for tokenization, as Jermaine shared with you, right, basically, when we need to… Train a language model, right?
Soon | NTU: similar to what we have seen in the, I think, in the…
Soon | NTU: previous session, right? We need to, pre-process our data, right, for number, or we need to do some normalization and scaling, and for categorical value.
Soon | NTU: we need to do some one-hot encoding and so on, okay? But today's topic is dealing with natural language, okay? So, what is so special about natural language is because the… we are dealing mainly with text, right? Text that
Soon | NTU: sequence data, write the language, okay? So we do not treat each of these words separately, but together they have some meaning, some semantics, okay? So that is why we need to
Soon | NTU: take this first step in the pre-processing when we're dealing with natural language, right? It's called a tokenization. Now.
Soon | NTU: First, in its very… So-called a basic
Soon | NTU: form, we can simply use the Python library, right? We have this, split, so we can use the Python split function to just basically tell you, oh, you know, tokenization is smoothly.
Soon | NTU: Splitting each of these wood.
Soon | NTU: In… The, the, the words in a sentence
Soon | NTU: In, separately, you know, and each of these words is what we call a token.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is the tokenization, example in this, simplest form. Without taking into account
Soon | NTU: A lot of things, like, as you notice, you know, there's this, Punctuation here, first off, right?
Soon | NTU: So this is something we can do.
Soon | NTU: off the shell from the Python library, alright? But, of course, if we want to have more meaningful tokenization, we need to go a step further, right? So, the second example of…
Soon | NTU: Using…
Soon | NTU: showing you this, tokenization is what we call the punctuation-based tokenization, okay, where we only look at… right, so in this case, we are looking at this, RE library regular expression in, Python, which is a very
Soon | NTU: Useful library for you to do a lot of, pattern searching in your text, okay?
Soon | NTU: You know, the text can be number, you know, you can use this library to do a lot of checking, you know, see, one example is whether the email is indeed contained valid email.
Soon | NTU: where your credit card indeed contain a valid credit card format, and so on, okay? So, in this case, we are using it to determine whether, you know, the token that we have extracted, you know, are basically a forward
Soon | NTU: from this sentence. So, in this case, you can see
Soon | NTU: Our original sentence is, natural language processing is fun.
Soon | NTU: Eskimijima.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but you can see the exclamation mark is Not included as…
Soon | NTU: part of the token list here, okay, which is slightly different from our Python version of the, tokenization.
Soon | NTU: method, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay? So now, sometimes the punctuation may or may not, be…
Soon | NTU: Very important, okay, in determining the meaning of your, sentence, Alright.
Soon | NTU: Okay, especially, let's say you have a very good use case sentiment analysis, alright? So, if you have
Soon | NTU: three exclamation marks, right? The model…
Soon | NTU: After training would think, oh, you know, there is some, weightage, you know?
Soon | NTU: being placed on the wood that is just before these three excavation marks. So what it is, okay? So based on that, it can have some kind of, implication as to the kind of sentiment that is, you know, for each of the sentence that the model is penalizing, okay? So, but in this case, tokenization, we don't need that.
Soon | NTU: Exclamation mark to be in our tokenization list, okay?
Soon | NTU: So now, for our, so-called NLP libraries, right, in
Soon | NTU: This, notebook, okay, we have, shortlisted two,
Soon | NTU: Very, commonly used, library.
Soon | NTU: So, very useful to, showcase, you know, what's the, the concept on tokenization and so on. Okay, so even though we have already seen how all this can be done using the basic Python library, but I think for more, meaningful.
Soon | NTU: NLP, so-called the, task, processing tasks, okay? So we need to really make use of this sophisticated library.
Soon | NTU: more than the Python library, you know, to give you a basic tokenization like what we have seen before, right? Now.
Soon | NTU: This NLP library, NLTK and spaCy, They come with, their own tokenizer.
Soon | NTU: Right, so let's… First, take a look at the NLTK, Natural Language Toolkit.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you go to run this, just see whether you are able to run it without any error here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so when I run it.
Soon | NTU: I did encounter some error, okay? It's just because, we have… Already, the library has some…
Soon | NTU: Been updated, a few times, and…
Soon | NTU: the link that we see here may be a bit of, outdated, okay? If you do encounter error in, like, this, okay, because I ever run a few times, so even if I have, a library, error here, it will not,
Soon | NTU: get any further error in the subsequent codes, okay? So you can replace this Again.
Soon | NTU: by… Okay, let me check what should be clear.
Soon | NTU: Do you have any error when you run your code?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yes.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me see what should be the,
Soon | NTU: Okay, let's… there are a few… Link.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let me… Okay, let me put in a chat.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you can… put the…
Soon | NTU: Sorry, yeah, my keyboard is not working.
Lik Hong Eng: Oh, it's… It's still the problem also, you can try… 100%.
Soon | NTU: Sorry, let me, restart my VS Code, so… It is hanging.
Soon | NTU: Okay, just give me a second.
Soon | NTU: I don't know why I just thought there was a lockup.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let me paste the command here.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: So… Let me run right from the beginning.
Soon | NTU: So that… the link… should be…
Soon | NTU: tag with some version number, right? So, over time, this library would have been, this is actually one of the model, language model, that come with the spaCy.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… We are preparing
Soon | NTU: both libraries at the same time, import them first, even though we are going to show the NL key kit first.
Soon | NTU: Right, so now I have already installed it before, okay? So hopefully it will help you to, I think, fix the error.
Soon | NTU: That, occur in this, quotebook 5.
Soon | NTU: Right? Does it help? Is the…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, so I hope, everyone have, are able to load that. Okay? So now, loading, this spec sheet…
Soon | NTU: library is one, because the spaC library does not come with a specific language model, okay? So, once we have successfully
Soon | NTU: loaded.
Soon | NTU: Okay, we have,
Soon | NTU: to load the specific language model which we are going to use for this notebook. So, in this case, we are only using a small
Soon | NTU: English.
Soon | NTU: Again, EN for English, this is a small. There are other…
Soon | NTU: language model in different languages. I think it can support
Soon | NTU: species support quite a lot of, foreign languages, not only English, okay? And it also comes with, medium as well as a large.
Soon | NTU: Model.
Soon | NTU: Again.
Soon | NTU: So, if you… one, again, if you check it out, I think for medium, it's called MD.
Soon | NTU: Lunch.
Soon | NTU: I'm not sure about the Avivation, but you can just go and ask the chat GPT, I think it's LG, for a large, okay? So we can,
Soon | NTU: Just try to use the other model to test it out, you know, the functionality in the… the notebook.
Soon | NTU: Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we load it, and then we put it in the NLP variable, and then this is how
Soon | NTU: we do the, tokenization, right? So somehow we have already, right? So with this…
Soon | NTU: It has some kind of, tokenization.
Soon | NTU: Right? So, as you can see, this NLP Behind the scene is…
Soon | NTU: able to do a lot of things, including tokenization. So after this function call, right, you know this doc contains the token that you want, okay? So here, we're going to display one by one, okay? So you can see, this is also one way of using the other more,
Soon | NTU: I wouldn't say sophisticated, but something more…
Soon | NTU: powerful than the Titan version, right? To do the tokenization, yeah, and this includes the estimation.
Soon | NTU: So whether we need to drop it or not, we will decide it.
Soon | NTU: Based on our use case list.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay? So for…
Soon | NTU: The next step is to do the tax normalization, right? So after you have done the pre-processing, first step is always the
Soon | NTU: tokenization, right? If you don't tokenize your sentence or your document content, you basically cannot go to the next step of doing stemming and
Soon | NTU: Limitization.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: So… Collectively, we call understanding and lammatization.
Soon | NTU: normalization, right? So, nothing to do with the data normalization we have seen before, okay? So, stamming, we have a few variants. So, the portal stammer and the snowball stammer. So, basically.
Soon | NTU: This is probably Easter.
Soon | NTU: enhanced, slightly improved version of the Porter Stammer. Okay, so basically, what you have seen before is, you know, you are looking at
Soon | NTU: Whether that's any prefake.
Soon | NTU: Suffix, you know, if you can find it, just chop it, right?
Soon | NTU: convenient. So… The end result, sometimes you could end up with a work which is not Not,
Soon | NTU: found in the dictionary, not valid, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: No. So, to make use of the library, you just have to import this, Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then… Do the, okay, so we have a cash…
Soon | NTU: words, okay, some sentence, some wording here, and then we go through this Porter stamp and the snowball stem. So, as you can see, the output are very, very close, right?
Soon | NTU: To be screened.
Soon | NTU: If you have a something-something Lee, Right.
Soon | NTU: you will just chop it, right? I don't know why you only chop at this, okay, but probably it will only detect, oh, if there's an L1, just remove it, right? You will not care what is in front, right? So, end up, you do not have a valid word in here.
Soon | NTU: Easily.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Fairly.
Soon | NTU: Win.
Soon | NTU: And the rest are… They don't seem to contain some prefix.
Soon | NTU: Damn.
Soon | NTU: There's a language, there's a question from Shed.
Soon | NTU: Is language up to our choice in snowball.
Soon | NTU: Yes, you can choose the language.
Soon | NTU: Oh… C.
Soon | NTU: But if you want to change the language, you have to make sure that you load the, correct,
Soon | NTU: So-called the, whatever things that you want to test, right?
Soon | NTU: let's say for German, you don't pass English words for testing, Okay.
Soon | NTU: So that one, you, you can, just…
Soon | NTU: Test it out using different languages.
Soon | NTU: So, for this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you can see.
Soon | NTU: All these are vegan.
Soon | NTU: Supported languages. Quite a lot.
Soon | NTU: Wing.
Soon | NTU: Okay? So you can, change it.
Soon | NTU: To… tornado.
Soon | NTU: If you know, let's say, French or
Soon | NTU: Hungarian, then you can do something more than just English words, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is the end result. Now, you can see some of the words are still retained.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: You know? So, for stammer, we don't really look at, like, like this lemmatization, which we're going to see in the next, section.
Soon | NTU: There's no… whether look up to a dictionary to check out whether I need to convert this into good.
Soon | NTU: Bad.
Soon | NTU: If it's a noun, you know, if it's a pro or noun, I need to convert it into singular now, and so on, okay? No further than that. I just basically… if there's a prefix, suffix, I will just chop it, you know, and take the word as a…
Soon | NTU: final token for the next step, okay? So now, in lemmatization.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so it always, also comes with this, inside the NLTK, so it's called a Word.
Soon | NTU: Net Demetizer.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so sometimes it can be very confusing, you know, one word net lymphatizer. So, would it be other, variant of the lymphatizer?
Soon | NTU: Okay, inside the NLTK, right? Well, probably, yeah, there are. Now, this word net lemmatizer, right, okay, they have already been, trained, okay.
Soon | NTU: And this is the…
Soon | NTU: WordNet, some kind of a corpus, okay, so to contain some information of the data which
Soon | NTU: the lemmatizer had been trained to recognize, right?
Soon | NTU: So, now… We are going to… bring in 2… So-called the, Model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so our… Compass.
Soon | NTU: As well as these… Tego.
Soon | NTU: Though… P-OS tagger.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now, the reason for that is, you know, this NLTK is a bit of, the design is based on some kind of,
Soon | NTU: You treat every word inside your… every token inside your sentence as a null by default.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you do that, right, so it's very difficult for you to do lemmatization, right? Because the treatment of lammatization on the wood
Soon | NTU: Verb.
Soon | NTU: In a noun, adverb, adjective.
Soon | NTU: Different, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that's why in this step.
Soon | NTU: It is going to convert whatever
Soon | NTU: This is a function that we need to build to tag each of the words inside here, the token inside this word input, okay, into some POS.
Soon | NTU: It means to… to recognize whether that token is a… Adjective, noun, verb, or adjective.
Soon | NTU: A verb, sorry. Okay?
Soon | NTU: So, if you've got to print it out, you know, you can, get… Okay, let me… Bookies.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so overall, most point.
Soon | NTU: pointer over the post tank. You can see there's some examples here, right?
Soon | NTU: So there's some example of… so this is a null.
Soon | NTU: Personality.
Soon | NTU: Okay, this person name. So this is, maybe this is,
Soon | NTU: Well, don't know what it means, okay? So, JJ means, could be adjective, right, describing some, object. This is a noun, singular, and so on, okay? So, we are only interested in extracting those words, okay?
Soon | NTU: That, the token reading list of word input, right? That are adjective, None, verb, and adverb.
Soon | NTU: And then, based on that, we tap the token accordingly, okay? Then the lemmatization can take over and do the next step, right? Because the…
Soon | NTU: The conversion of this token.
Soon | NTU: to the base form, right, count a lot on whether the POS tag is adjective, noun, verb, and
Soon | NTU: adverb, okay? So, these are the… Words that we have,
Soon | NTU: the original words, right? Okay, so let's see…
Soon | NTU: Okay, sorry, the words are inside here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so these are the words. Let me copy this.
Soon | NTU: And then paste it here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that we can see, compare it, okay? So, lammatized words are like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the original words are here. Okay, so, as you can see.
Soon | NTU: some of the words, some of the token, okay, call it words, okay? Some of the tokens are…
Soon | NTU: Transform into a simpler form.
Soon | NTU: Okay, running.
Soon | NTU: become run.
Soon | NTU: RAM is still RAM, okay? Runs become run, and so on, okay? So, as you can see, this is how… okay, so this is a…
Soon | NTU: Ural now.
Soon | NTU: So it… I think mouse is singular now.
Soon | NTU: Fit is poorer.
Soon | NTU: And food is singular.
Soon | NTU: better.
Soon | NTU: It will not be… B-E-T-T, you know, bad E means instead is become well.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Not better, best, you know, there's no such, some kind of a comparative, circle meaning in a word, okay? Everything is transformative well. So this is what we call the, lemmatization example.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but unfortunately, there's some limitation on how accurate
Soon | NTU: this lemonization from NLTK works. Okay, as you can see, Why this is not run.
Soon | NTU: This is a past 10, okay? But so, if you go to print out all orders, right.
Soon | NTU: the words, again, you notice this rain is actually tagged under now.
Soon | NTU: Okay, that's why you… it is now…
Soon | NTU: No further action will be taken if this is a singular
Soon | NTU: If it's approval, probably the S will be chopped off, okay? Okay, so there's, some limitation.
Soon | NTU: in the clematizer of an NLTK.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: So… How about…
Soon | NTU: Using another, sentence, another example sentence to illustrate the, this concept of lemmatization, and see whether
Soon | NTU: it is able to transform this into limit times tokens, okay? So, now this works, right?
Soon | NTU: here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this basically, helped to format your,
Soon | NTU: so-call the token nicely, okay, so that they are in the column format, rather than zigzag, okay? So now, you have an original text here, and a lemmatized words are like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: So, this is, for… Past tense, she'll become the present.
Soon | NTU: tends best.
Soon | NTU: rural now become singular, and so on, okay? So, as you can see, Is this, is this quite…
Soon | NTU: Better than the… the previous?
Soon | NTU: version.
Soon | NTU: Do you think it's better?
Soon | NTU: You can't tell, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, so, I'm also quite curious, okay, so…
Soon | NTU: In the length of the… Okay, so… 18th, hello.
Soon | NTU: AI will come into the… Take action, okay, after a while. Okay, so, why not I run this?
Soon | NTU: And then…
Soon | NTU: Okay, it's just… it's slightly different, right, from the first time we run it, right? So, as you can see, if this is a verb, right.
Soon | NTU: You have to be in a…
Soon | NTU: present tense, right? If this is now, no action taken.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the only thing that will be taken is when it is a poorer.
Soon | NTU: Right? Then you become a singular.
Soon | NTU: Verb will be converted to a present tense. Adverb No question they can.
Soon | NTU: And then, this is an adjective, right? Comparative.
Soon | NTU: you'll be…
Soon | NTU: put into a common word, okay, based on what is inside the dictionary, okay? So this is program, you read.
Soon | NTU: length times into the singular equivalent, right? Okay, so this is something you can, do to check out the, so-called, whether each of the different
Soon | NTU: variant of the lemmatization from different library, whether it's a
Soon | NTU: Able to help you in doing the tokenization, stemming, and also the, lemmatization.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: So that completes the first part.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so these are the second part of the, language modeling.
germayne: Okay, you guys need break?
germayne: Right, I can't see everybody's face.
germayne: Yeah, you guys need break. You guys want a break?
germayne: Okay, I can see everybody's head. Okay, okay. Then, let's do… let's do 5 minutes, lah, let's do 5 minutes break.
germayne: Okay, so we… we come back at 8.14, we come back at 8.14.
Lily Seah: Soon, can I ask you a question?
Soon | NTU: Yes.
Lily Seah: you know, I… I followed the… the VS Code.
Lily Seah: And the part on the striped beds are hanging on their feet.
Lily Seah: Somehow, my…
Lily Seah: my results came out to be a little bit different from yours, so I wonder what's the reason. Like, the word stripe
Lily Seah: Yours changed to a present tense, but mine did not.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me run it again, huh?
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me share my screen.
Soon | NTU: Lily, are you referring to this?
Lily Seah: I, I, I didn't see your screen.
Lily Seah: Are you…
Soon | NTU: prevented this.
Lily Seah: Yes, yes, my did not change to a present tense.
Lily Seah: So I wonder what is the difference, I mean, my, my, my code, my notebook?
Soon | NTU: Where is the post tag?
Soon | NTU: Is it book?
Lily Seah: No, it's adjut… it's adjective.
Lily Seah: So… So, I mean, it's,
Lily Seah: It's not, the same, like, sometimes it can be different.
Soon | NTU: Boom.
Soon | NTU: Our codebase are the same, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me check if there are…
Soon | NTU: Do you load the… the new version of the…
Soon | NTU: the English language model, the small model.
Soon | NTU: Just know.
Lily Seah: At which point, actually, there was multiple errors, and I got the agent, the AI, to correct it for me, so I do not know what…
Lily Seah: whether that was the latest, but I think I… now I note that…
Lily Seah: the Python environment, I use ML. Does it matter? Yours, I know, is DL.
Soon | NTU: You use MLR.
Lily Seah: Yes.
Soon | NTU: Is it possible for you to use the… Yeah, then we can educate.
Lily Seah: I…
Soon | NTU: Compare apple to apple.
Lily Seah: DL, I don't have it on my list, I have to go and set it up.
Lily Seah: Okay, so this may make a difference, is it? The environment?
Thue Leong Meng Adrian: I think it's a 3.7.
Soon | NTU: Oh, it's 3x7.
Soon | NTU: It should be in 3.7,
Lily Seah: Oh, okay, I haven't seen it.
Soon | NTU: right?
Soon | NTU: try whether, if you use a DL environment, whether you.
Lily Seah: Okay, so this… this may make a difference, so I… that's what I want to know.
Soon | NTU: And also, trying to use the preset one.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Soon, I can see that in the line 4, right, so instead of ending with NCore WebSM, if you add the dash 3.7.1, I think it'll just…
Soon | NTU: Taesun?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yeah, so that is the original one, right? So you just need to add the 371 at the end, dash 371.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, yeah, correct. If you do… you encounter error in your… in your codes, right, when you run it, so just command it.
Soon | NTU: And then you… Because this one, you are…
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Even in the OEM, you just need to add…
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: what I mean is, even in the original one, you just add the dash 3.7.1 at the end.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: In the original code, and it will still work.
Soon | NTU: ed to where?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: At the end.
Soon | NTU: at the N.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: No, no, in that…
Soon | NTU: Here?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Line 4, line 4.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Line 4, line 4.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so line 4, you are going to add something.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Translate.
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yeah, dash 3.7.1, just add .7.on me.
Soon | NTU: Okay, over here,
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Yes, yes. If you're able to run it, then, with a suffix of 371, there's also something like this.
Soon | NTU: Are you referring to this?
Jagatheeswaran Rajagurunathan: Yep.
Soon | NTU: Let me, let me try. I have not tried that before.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: to comment.
Soon | NTU: Yes.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Need to uncomment.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Yep.
Soon | NTU: Yes, so it still works?
Soon | NTU: Beautiful.
Soon | NTU: He still works.
Soon | NTU: Okay, good, good, good point.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, Elite, you let me know if you, still encounter errors, yeah.
Lily Seah: Okay, okay, I'll set up the DL.
Lily Seah: Thanks.
Soon | NTU: You're welcome.
germayne: Okay, everyone back?
germayne: Let me share my screen.
germayne: Okay, ready? Ready to continue?
germayne: Okay, so I think for the next part, we will now talk a bit about some of the traditional mechanisms. So I think there are some questions on, you know, you guys are maybe thinking that, okay, maybe some of the processing might not make sense, and I think we will get a bit of insights.
germayne: Okay, so I think we are just going to talk a bit about the different, various language models, okay? So most likely, you will have seen this before, right? And here, what we are trying to define is that
germayne: Usually, language model is formulated in a way where we actually want to predict
germayne: some kind of words within a sequence of words, right? So, for example, here you can see that, you know, what we want to train a model, a language model, is we want to have the model predict and fill in the blanks based on certain vocabularies, okay?
germayne: Obviously, modern language… modern large language model is actually what we call a decoding task. So, essentially, it will try to predict the… the word at the very end, right, given a sequence of words, I want to predict what is the probability across all of my given vocabulary, and what is that word.
germayne: obviously, back then, I would say a couple of years back, actually, encoder models.
germayne: are actually more prominent, right? In a sense whereby they were actually formulated to fill in the blanks, not necessarily at the end of the word. You could actually remove the cat here, and it will try to predict, out of all the vocab, what is the probability of the… out of all the vocabulary, what are the words
germayne: So it was actually formulated like a classification task. Again, it's a multi-classification, you can see here, right? Because I'm trying to predict, out of all of my blanks, what is the… what is the probability out of all my vocab, which word actually has a set of probability.
germayne: Okay, and obviously the language model, because it's a multi-classification, right, from a… from a… from the modern large language model or language model's perspective, they will actually have some kind of probability, so you will see that it's actually a probability distribution, right? And…
germayne: The idea here is that it was actually a bit magical, because when the model was actually trained to fill in the blanks, which we call it the mass language modeling, actually the model somehow learned about the linguistic property of words.
germayne: If you ask me why I don't think people solve the why yet, it's just very magical that by training the model on tasks like mass language modeling, or training on predicting the next word, the model just magically knows about the linguistic properties of words and the meaning of words.
germayne: Right, so it's actually very, very, very magical.
germayne: But of course, historically, it was not always like that, right? So, architecturally, you know, we actually moved from RNN and LSTM to transformer-based.
germayne: Before neural network, there's actually something called the engram. Ngram is typically a preprocessing mechanism, but you can also actually use it to predict the next word.
germayne: Right? And it's actually just using simple statistics. You just basically convert, and I think you can see from the notebook later, you're just basically converting the original input data into an engram.
germayne: And what we do is we can basically just use the statistics to understand the probability of the next word.
germayne: Right? So, obviously, what we are trying to show here is the… the heuristical… it's more of, like, a data traditional method using statistics, right? But then, after that, you know, when we have deep learning, because recurring neural network and RSTM, which we will see more on Thursday, it actually works on sequential data.
germayne: So what this means is that anything that has a sequential dependency, and because Words has a sequence, it is actually very good at predicting the long-term dependency, right? It has some kind of memory in terms of the sequences, and of course, later ISTM is introduced to solve the
germayne: Problem that, you know, they call it the vanishing gradient.
germayne: As well as the fact that it tends to forget about long sequence.
germayne: Right? And obviously, RNN and LSTM used to be state-of-the-art many, many, many, many years ago, until transformer-based architecture came, right?
germayne: We probably can talk a bit about Transformer, but the story here is that Transformer basically has this attention mechanism, right? The attention mechanism is basically an ability to weigh the importance of the sequence of words relative to each other, right, in order to determine the context.
germayne: So it doesn't have the constraints of RNN and LSTM, where things have to be done sequentially, right? It can do everything all at once, because anyway, the positions are encoded.
germayne: Okay, I'm talking about some… you know, you can hear me talk about all this blabbering, but then it might not make sense now, right? And I don't think it's important today, but the whole point is that these are the… the… how the…
germayne: NLP landscape has evolved. And obviously, obviously, transformer-based solutions are obviously the best today. But then the natural question here would be that, does that mean that everything else we learn is useless? Maybe not necessarily, right?
germayne: again, I think this has very similar… you know, today we'll talk about some very basic traditional methods, but I think, again, one similar problem here with RNN and LSTM is that
germayne: If you are, like, usually in the middle, nobody will want to use you, right? It's either you use the best, or you will use the simplest. Similar theme has linear regression, right? Linear regression is still used anyways.
germayne: Right.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Wait, let me… wait, huh?
germayne: I lost my button.
germayne: Okay, so back to… back to Ngram. So essentially, n-gram, you can think of a, you know, a mechanism to
germayne: just convert the data into these different end sequence. So a unigram, essentially, is the original data. So if you look at… you can look at this simple example. This is our sentence. The sentence is, this is big data AI book. So a unigram will essentially be the original representation. A bigram, you notice is that there's actually the overlapping
germayne: tuper of work, pair, right? So this tuper becomes, this is, is big, big data.
germayne: data, AI, and then AI book, right? So you can basically see we are actually overlapping the tokens, the next token, and then you have the trigram. So basically, n-gram is just that, you know, you are defining from unigram all the way to Ngram, and
germayne: This is the mechanism where we can actually use n-grams in order to compute the statistic of which word is likely to be next.
germayne: Okay, and the idea here is that if I can always see is…
germayne: coming after this, and if I see this multiple times, I can basically say that there's a high probability that is comes after this, right? So this is, like, the old-school traditional method. Of course, I don't think people use engrams now to predict sequence. If you want to predict sequence, most likely you can do, you can use the transformer architecture, right? You can use any of the pre-trained models.
germayne: But… The… the idea is that
germayne: Ngram is usually used in other
germayne: methods for preprocessing data. So obviously, if, let's say, I think I talk about something like retrieval, for example. So if, let's say, you're building some kind of recommender, you want to have a retrieval task, actually, engram is still used for query matching, for example, right? They still have a parameter to do Ngram.
germayne: So, not really used for predicting the next sequence, most likely used for…
germayne: query expansion, right? Something like in your recommender system, which we will not talk about, right? But you can see a lot of… a lot to do with the query. Usually, it expands the query to do matching, right? And yeah, so actually it's still being used, although not in the way that it was done for predicting the next sequence.
germayne: Okay, so now we are getting into the meat of today's lesson.
germayne: So the idea here is that somehow, in order for us to reason about the linguistic
germayne: meaning of words. We need to somehow represent them in a vector space.
germayne: Okay? So I want to ask you guys, if you talk about vector space minus what we talk about on Saturday, right?
germayne: what lesson actually has this similar concept about thinking about, you know, identifying things that are similar in a vector space? Who remembers?
germayne: This shouldn't be a new concept, right?
germayne: So, what are some of the things that we learned before, from 3.1 all the way to 3.8?
germayne: What… where did we actually talk about vector space?
germayne: So essentially, the idea is, if I can think about points that are similar together, then they must be similar. Where do we actually see this?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Computer vision.
germayne: Okay, I wasn't expecting that, but not wrong, correct? That's also correct. What else?
Zac Ang: ECA.
germayne: PCA.
germayne: Mmm… also… also not wrong.
germayne: also not wrong, but I'm also not expecting PCA. What else?
germayne: What else?
Zac Ang: K, KNN.
germayne: Yes, yes, KNN, KNN.
germayne: What else?
germayne: Still got one more.
germayne: the hint is clustering. What do we learn in clustering?
Lily Seah: Unsupervised learning.
germayne: Correct. So what's the ALGO, specifically?
germayne: In unsupervised.
germayne: Oh, actually, all of it.
germayne: Yeah, actually, all of it. Yeah, I think correct. I think, Lily, that's the correct answer. So, so you… so actually it's not… it's not… it's not a new concept, right? Where if somehow we can represent these vectors, again, right, mathematically, when we say vector, it's just the… the matrix, so essentially it's just a… oh, sorry.
germayne: So if you talk about vector, we are just basically saying, like, it's a matrix.
germayne: Right? And where we have the element X1, X2, all the way to Xn.
germayne: Right? Where n is your dimension. So I'm going to write this. So this is your dimension. So basically, this is the n dimension, right? So your data is projected in this dimension.
germayne: So, this concept is not very different from whatever that we learned. Somehow, if we can represent them in some kind of space, then the intuition is that if they are similar, if they are near… if they are near each other, again, this example is three-dimensional.
germayne: If, let's say, two points are similar, then…
germayne: actually, they should be… they should be close together, and of course, of course, the… the algorithms that are trained to output this vector representation are done and motivated in a way, of course, by the loss function, by gradient descent, if you are using deep learning, but they are motivated in a way to
germayne: End quote.
germayne: These factors to be close to each other.
germayne: Okay? So, the whole concept here is very, very similar, it's just that now, we need to answer how do we actually convert text into this vector representation?
germayne: Right, so it's not the first time that we are seeing this vector representation. You guys mentioned we've seen them in TCA.
germayne: Yes, I would say it's also correct, right? You have some kind of data that transformed them, except that the property was orthogonal, right? The components is orthogonal, which we talked about that in PCA. KNN, K means we didn't do any transformation, but the data is represented by its raw features.
germayne: But today, right, we want to convert somehow from your original text
germayne: We want to convert them into some kind of vector, which is this representation, right? And this is, of course, in n dimension. And the idea here, again, is that
germayne: intuitively, the documents, again, right, we start to use this term, documents. So, in…
germayne: you can think of documents like your paragraphs or your books, but essentially the idea here is that if there is Document 1, D1, here, and document D2,
germayne: is this… if these two documents is similar in terms of meaning, in terms of semantics, we want to put them very close together. Of course, we're not going to semantics yet, but the idea here is, how do I actually convert them to vector space? And that's going to be the whole next
germayne: thing that we're going to talk about. Of course, we're going to start simple first. We're going to start very, very simple, right? Before we even think about very complex deep learning, how can we actually do them? How can we actually do it in a way where it's easy?
germayne: is… what are the basic ideas to actually encode them into a document? Do we start to see that?
germayne: Okay, I keep losing my… Ugh, I keep losing my button. Okay, we are.
germayne: Okay, so we're going to… we're going to start very, very simple.
germayne: So, the idea here is we are going to start with a lexical mechanism. So, lexical, essentially, we are not talking about semantics. We are purely still looking at word matching, right? So, the idea here is we're going to start with what we call a bag of words.
germayne: So a back of words is really… we want to represent every document. A document is basically your paragraph or your book, right? A document. We want to represent them using a collection of words.
germayne: So now, if I want to ask you guys, a very… what could be an easy way to represent them is actually to count the frequency of the words, correct? So if, let's say, a book says dog and cats.
germayne: 1 million times. Then these two books that has the highest number of dogs and cats must be similar, right? That's the first intuition. So we just do very simple stuff. Just like your feature engineering, we start with something very, very simple. So what we do is, in back of words, we actually use the count frequency. And if you think about it.
germayne: We can actually encode our book, right? If, let's say, in your document D1, document D2, and document D3, these are all your documents, right? Basically, each row, our data, our original data, they are all a sentence, right? You can see here, D1 is the dog is happy. It's a very simple document.
germayne: Again, a document can be very long, can be a book, can be a paragraph, but here we're just making it as a sentence. So D1 is, the doc is happy. Again, we tokenize by using the white space tokenizer, very simple mechanism. So we split.
germayne: each of the document into its respective token. So the is one vocab, doc is one vocab, is is one vocab, happy is one vocab.
germayne: Second document is the child makes the dog happy, and the third document is the dog makes the child happy. So you notice that D2 and D3 is actually
germayne: Simil… Sorry, sorry.
germayne: D2 is the child makes the dog happy, and D3 is the dog makes the child happy. Okay, so it's slightly different.
germayne: Right, from a meaning standpoint, it's slightly different, but it's almost the same.
germayne: But what we are saying here is we tokenize them, we split them into its own representation. So you can see here that each token essentially makes up the vocabulary. So the total subset of all these data, we take the unique token, and you notice that that becomes the
germayne: the vocabulary. So, hypothetically, in these three documents, our vocab is actually child, dog, happy, is, next door.
germayne: And what we can do is, for each… for each document, we just basically count the number of occurrence each of the words appear. So, notice what happens is that the total number of unique words becomes the total number of dimension.
germayne: Can follow, right? So far? Out of these 3 words, we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. So basically, we are mapping them to
germayne: In the real number space, we are mapping them to 6, the 6th dimension. So you notice that your vector is a 1x6 vector.
germayne: Right? For one document, I have a sequence of 6 tokens.
germayne: Can follow so far?
germayne: Right, so you can see, right, if we take the count frequency, we basically can map the data for document Y, it becomes a representation of 011101.
germayne: Document 2 is 111012, and then document 3 becomes 111012.
germayne: Okay? And you get to see, actually, that, oh, from Document 2 and Document 3's perspective, it's actually exactly the same. The similarity is exactly the same.
germayne: You can see, right?
germayne: Because the total appearance of the words is the same, even though the meaning is slightly different.
germayne: So, what's the takeaway here?
germayne: Takeaway here is somehow we can encode
germayne: Again, we are bringing from tech space, we are mapping them to a vector space.
germayne: Right? But… Will you guys say that D2 and D3 semantically is the same? Is it semantically the same?
germayne: not exactly the same, right? One is coming from the fact that the child is important, because the child is the one that makes the dog happy, right? The third one is from the… the…
germayne: Doc's perspective, where the dog makes the child happy.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: But from this mechanism, you can see that
germayne: It encodes them in a similar manner.
germayne: Okay, I want to ask you guys, any other issues with this?
germayne: Anybody has any intuition, any issues with this?
germayne: What, what other potential problem, okay, this can have, this, this, this is problematic?
germayne: Any guesses?
Zac Ang: The sequence is wrong.
germayne: Sequence is wrong.
Zac Ang: There's no sequences, the order is lost.
germayne: Oh, okay, okay, fair point, yes. Sequence is not. Okay, what else? Any other issues? Potential issues?
germayne: Correct? I think that's correct. So sequence is… sequence is not maintained.
germayne: What else?
germayne: Any other potential problem?
germayne: In this example.
germayne: Is there a problem with the and is?
germayne: If the book has a lot of the, a lot of is.
germayne: It will also capture all these, right?
germayne: So then the question here is, oh, maybe I should remove them, right? Should I remove the stop word?
germayne: Yeah, maybe you can.
germayne: But then there's so many stop words. Do I need to maintain a lease?
germayne: Okay, so keep that, keep that, keep that in mind first, for now.
germayne: Okay, so essentially this is what we call the count vectorizer. Very, very simple algorithm.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, so, so, so, just on the slide,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: The… is there a concern if there are too many… too many, too many words?
germayne: Oh, exactly, exactly. So, correct, correct, correct, exactly, Noel, that's a good point. So, that's why your processing method, right?
germayne: Child, childs, children… well, each one, each one all separate?
germayne: Then you imagine there's so many forms per word, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: Meat. Meat.
germayne: make… Wow, 3 radii.
germayne: Well, you'll just explode.
germayne: So now, back to the original point that was asked in the chat. Hey, do I need to process the data? So now, do you want to process the data?
germayne: Or you don't process, your vector is going to be so big.
germayne: Super high dimension.
germayne: And then what's another problem? So back to you, Noel. So just now you say, right, okay.
germayne: Feels like the dimension will become very big. If the dimension is very big, what do you think will happen?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: The question you asked on Saturday, like, yeah, it's like, you get.
germayne: No.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: No, he's like…
germayne: Not yet, not yet. Haven't.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, yeah, no. Okay.
germayne: So let's say, hypothetically, right, let's say, right, I'm sure you guys know that if you were to take all the unique number of words that we have, I'm sure you guys can see that it's actually going to be very big.
germayne: Millions also possible, right? So your dimension is something n by… I don't know how many million here, very long. So what do you think is a problem?
germayne: So if, let's say, I want to put the… the dog is happy, my representation is N by a million, right? Because I have all the… all the vocab. What do you think… what do you think will be the representation of D1? What will happen to D1? Anybody knows?
germayne: Because in reality, it won't just be 6 words, right?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: euros.
germayne: Exactly, a lot of zeros, correct. So you realize that this whole thing is, like, a lot of zeros, right? It's very sparse.
germayne: Exactly.
germayne: Correct? So we're storing a lot of nonsense. I mean, a lot of gaps, lah, a lot of zeros. Correct? Very sparse.
germayne: Fantastic. So you guys can see the potential problem with this.
germayne: So the resulting matrix is going to be a very sparse matrix.
germayne: Okay, so this is actually what we call the count vectorizer. You can do this in scikit-learn.
germayne: Right? Of course, this is a simple mechanism, right? And… you guys already discussed about the problem. Okay, so we want to answer the open question just now. We have an open question, correct? The open question that we have was that…
germayne: We noticed that the stop words are there.
germayne: Right? And then you can argue that, okay, sure, I can… I can remove the stop words, but then, can we actually have a mechanism to…
germayne: You know, maybe we use the data to remove the stop words instead, right? So we have a problem with stop words. So what we're going to do? We are going to improve upon count vectorizer.
germayne: Okay, we are going to introduce this concept. Okay, before we go there, just to give you guys one last illustration.
germayne: So this is actually how the count vectorizer, again, will look like.
germayne: If you have 3 documents, 3 sentences here, right, 3 documents, what you can basically do is each of the unique words will become the word index, which actually forms the vocabulary.
germayne: And what will happen is that if your vocabulary is very big, which most likely will be.
germayne: then you're going to have very sparse matrices. Okay, so this is actually what the count vectorizer do.
germayne: So we want to move one step to introduce this concept called TF-IDF.
germayne: Okay, very, very important concept.
germayne: Because it's still being used.
germayne: Everywhere.
germayne: Okay? So…
germayne: Now, the idea here is that we know that there are words that are meaningless, we know that if, let's say, certain words appears many times, the term frequency will actually count it, right? So what the term frequency does is that the term frequency actually counts how many times a word appears in a document.
germayne: So it is within document, okay? So I want to… I want to… I want you guys to take note, it is within the document. So if you go back again, you can see, the first sentence, this is good. So basically, within a doc, we just count how many times these appear.
germayne: is appear, good appeal. And then we do the same for this is bad. Then we do the same as this is awesome.
germayne: So, term frequency is always counting the number of appearances within a document. Now, what we want to do is we want to use this thing called the inverse document frequency.
germayne: The intuition for this is very straightforward.
germayne: If a word appears across every document, again, this is across every document.
germayne: this is within a document, right? The intuition here is very simple. If a word appears many times across the
germayne: Every document, then basically it must be a useless word.
germayne: I'll repeat again.
germayne: A stop word is basically like, oh, this is, you know, like, those stop words, right? This is going to… this probably will appear in a lot of documents, because it's a stop word.
germayne: Agreed? So basically, the information from this is actually largely redundant. That's the concept.
germayne: If this appears across every document, then there's nothing for me to differentiate between the documents.
germayne: Right? But if, let's say, something like dot.
germayne: Will every document have dogs? Maybe not. Maybe dogs… maybe a document that focuses on animals would have tendency to talk about dogs. Maybe a handbook to train your puppies would have a lot of
germayne: keywords about DOW. So the idea is.
germayne: the idea, again, right, to take away for IDF is, I want to penalize the word, right? If the word always appears across document.
germayne: then it's most likely a, like, a stop word. So I'm going to, I'm going to say it's not important. And it's basically the formula here, the math, right, the IDF, is we're just going to take the log, the logarithm of it.
germayne: Right? The total number of documents in Corpus D that contains the term divided… sorry, the total number of documents in the numerator and the denominator is the total number of… the number of documents which contains the term, and we take the logarithm. So essentially, here, what we are seeing is that if a term like this
germayne: Like this.
germayne: appears many times across every document, you can see that this is going to get… this is going to penalize. We're going to… we are going to put the weight to be very small.
germayne: But if something like dock, which is a very rare word.
germayne: That appears very rarely across all the documents, then the weight for this will be very high.
germayne: And of course, the good news is IDF, we can just pre-compute this, because it will be at token level, right? For every token, we will compute the IDF.
germayne: So you can see, right, these mechanisms allow us, in a way, to use the data to compute the frequency of a word without
germayne: storing a list of stop words. But of course, you can still store. Scikit-learn allows you to still define a stop word, but then there might be too many stop words for you to capture, so maybe you can use this mechanism in order to penalize words that always appears, because they are not very important.
germayne: And you can see in this picture, this idea, again, is the same thing that we do.
germayne: We have two documents, D1, And D2,
germayne: And what we want to do here is, by using the TF-IDF,
germayne: the term frequency, inverse document frequency, the TF-IDF, what we are going to do again is, Oops, sorry.
germayne: what we are going to do is, we are going to calculate the frequency, right, the term frequency, the number of times it appears, divided by the total number of terms in the document. So we take the weight of each of the terms, right, the term frequency, right, you can see, we take the weight.
germayne: the occurrence of the weight across the terms, and what we're going to do is we're going to take the IDF, which is pre-computed across all the documents, right? So for each of it, we know that, obviously, you can see the weight here is, like, zero, right? Here is all zero, right? Because this has appeared many times.
germayne: So what we are going to do is we're going to take the weight, and we're going to multiply by the term frequency. So basically, again, what it does is that, mathematically, it pulls down the words that does not have any meaning.
germayne: Okay? So then your vector is going to automatically
germayne: Reduce the weight on words that are meaningless, because they could appear many times, and they might just over-inflate the representation of the vector.
germayne: Now, in practice, is TF-IDF actually being used? It depends, right? Again, it depends. If, let's say, you know, you want to start with simple, TF-IDF usually works for lexical matches, right? If you're looking in terms of keyword matches.
germayne: it works very well. A lot of retriever systems that uses BM25 actually is an updated version of TF-IDF, very similar to TF-IDF, where, again, we penalize words that appear across documents, right, but then we…
germayne: give higher weightage to unique words. So BM25, used in a lot of retriever systems, still uses this concept. So not completely useless, still industry standard. Recommended systems still use it for lexical matching.
germayne: Okay, pause here first so far. So far, quite easy, right? Quite easy to understand, right? So, essentially, you can see this mechanism.
germayne: You know, without even doing something complex, we can actually convert them to a vector space. We are essentially able to map a text data
germayne: We're going to map them to some kind of, dimension space, right? N dimension space, where n is defined by your vocab size.
germayne: Okay? So here you can see removing or stop words is important.
germayne: removal of common, you know, converting your language back to the common keywords is also important, right? Especially for traditional methods, because the… the length of the vocab size grows according to your vocab, your unique words.
germayne: Okay? So this is a very simple mechanism.
germayne: Now, once we converted them to vector, so you can see everything becomes a vector representation, right here, here's a vector, so you can see this is a vector.
germayne: Now, we need to answer one thing. How do we actually measure the similarity?
germayne: Anybody knows any similarity measure that we learned?
germayne: So let's say if I have two vectors, This is a two-dimensional example.
germayne: How do we measure similarity? Anybody, anybody knows?
germayne: Is that something that we learned before?
germayne: distance.
germayne: What distance? Do you guys remember the exact name of the distance?
germayne: What did we learn?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Alien distance, huh?
germayne: Euclidean, yeah, so Euclidean is one.
germayne: Okay, so we learned about the distance, but today we are going to introduce something different. We're not going to use distancing, okay? We are going to use a different…
germayne: Similarity metric.
germayne: Okay, so we're going to introduce this, it's called cosine similarity.
germayne: So the idea of cosine similarity, basically, we think about this from an angle, angle perspective. So if I have two vectors, vector X, which is here, and I have vector Y,
germayne: essentially, I can measure the cosine similarity, right? And what the cosine similarity will tell me, that this is theta, right? We'll basically see that if the angle is very, very, very close to 1,
germayne: Right, cosine of angle, close to 0, cosine similarity close to 1, then this tells me that the vectors are similar.
germayne: Okay? And here you can see different example, right? But the idea here is that using cosine similarity, the larger the cosine similarity, it tells us that, you know, they are actually similar within the space.
germayne: Okay? There are many reasons why we don't use distance metric, right? There are many, many reasons. One specific reason is that Euclidean distance doesn't work well in high dimension vectors. Usually, cosine… usually for NLP, cosine similarity is used
germayne: Most of the time. Another reason you will find, if you were to research, right, you will find that cosine similarity actually removes away the
germayne: the length of the vector, right? So essentially, we are not looking at the length, we are only looking at the angle.
germayne: From an angle perspective. And the reason for that is because of the way neural networks are trained. So typically, again, I'm just going to give verbal, you can just write it down for now, it will not make sense, and probably will not be taught in this whole course, but the idea is that usually when you train neural networks to do embedding, which we will see later.
germayne: the embedding might capture certain information about the popularity of the embedings of the vector. So what usually you want is you do not want to
germayne: You do not want to use the magnitude when you calculate the similarity. So what you want is, you want to do a… you want to do cosine similarity.
germayne: And if you guys remember, if you guys remember, in neural network, if you guys remember, we always do dot products. You always take the width, and you do a dot product. So, usually when people train models to create embeddings in order to maximize cosine similarity, what they usually do is because they will do a dot product, and mathematically.
germayne: In order to make dot product similar to cosine similarity, cosine similarity.
germayne: Usually, you have to do a normalization, an L2 norm.
germayne: So you'll do a normalization on the embedding vector so that it will be equivalent to cosine similarity. But long story short, most of the time, people use cosine similarity in order to reason about the similarity between two embedings, or two vectors, right, between X and Y.
germayne: Okay? And you will notice that this is the same concept that was taught on
germayne: Saturday. When you have a… when you want to retrieve documents that are similar, you want to retrieve chunks that are similar, you need to think about who is close, right?
germayne: How do I know which chunk is similar? If I asked about doc here, I would expect another document about dogs to be similar, right? Cat, maybe dogs, cat, whatever, right? Maybe a book about computer science would be something that is far away.
germayne: So, again, cosine similarity, very common. Many historical reasons why cosine similarity is used, but take away.
germayne: Is that dot product is similar to cosine similarity if it's normalized.
germayne: Okay, but yes, we use cosine similarity.
germayne: So you can see that cosine similarity is here. Quite easy to calculate.
germayne: Right, you can basically see from the math here is that it's just like a dot product divided by the unit norm. That's basically equivalent to cosine similarity.
germayne: Okay, so you can see here the example is actually very similar, right? Apple, banana, they are fruits. So from a linguistic standpoint, we expect them to be close together. Cat and dog, men and women, right? So basically, you can see in this example.
germayne: a good… Encoding… a good encoding will actually capture the similarity of the words in this space.
germayne: Right? So, I would expect apple and banana to be close, cat and dog to be closer, right? But then, if I were to measure cosine similarity between apple, if I take apple and dog, obviously it's not going to be close, as compared to apple and banana, right? Apple and banana, you can see it's going to be closer. Apple and banana is going to be something like that.
germayne: Correct?
germayne: So, you can see that this actually allows us to measure, you know, between two vectors, whether they are similar or not. And I want to ask you guys a question.
germayne: So if, let's say, we were to use…
germayne: the TF-IDF, do you think it can capture the similarity of semantics?
germayne: Can you capture semantics?
germayne: I see people shaking no, right? Because obviously, TF, IDF, and count vectorizer is just looking at the pure word, right? We are just encoding it word. So, we need something smarter, which we will see later on. We need… we somehow need a neural network to train to know that, okay.
germayne: If two words always appears with each other, then maybe linguistically they're similar.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Intuitive, right, so far?
germayne: Now, I want to take a pause here before we go to the next one. So if, let's say, today, right, we were to train a convolutional neural network, let's go back again to last week.
germayne: if I have a picture of Me.
germayne: I have a picture of a dog.
germayne: Am I drawing not bad, right?
germayne: And I have a picture of a lady.
germayne: From a picture perspective. And if we remove the fully connected layer.
germayne: Essentially, here we have the feature map, and I encode them all into vectors.
germayne: Can I actually say that I would expect
germayne: The resulting vector of a human and a woman to be similar as compared to a dog?
germayne: I want you guys to think first,
germayne: So, if you guys remember last week.
germayne: We talk about image, go into the convolutional, so here it learns about the features to extract out.
germayne: Would you expect that the man would be similar to the human versus a dog?
Zac Ang: Yes.
germayne: Why is that? Why is that so?
Zac Ang: The man should be similar to the woman.
germayne: Why? Do you have any intuition? Why do you think that would be so?
Zac Ang: Because it has…
germayne: features, yeah, yeah, yeah.
germayne: So maybe the model might see that there's a face shape, you know, doesn't have ears, got hair, you know, if the edge extracted has the hair, maybe there's a concept about the eyes.
germayne: You know?
germayne: Correct? So, yes. So the idea here is buy right.
germayne: a lot of these encoding… so here's the encoding step, right? So the model should be able to encode features that should be similar.
germayne: Alright.
germayne: So you can… if you do a similarity here, you should be able to expect that the feature map between the men and the women should be more similar as compared to men and dog.
germayne: If not, maybe your model learning something else, I don't know. Kubila, right?
germayne: Okay, so you guys should now start to understand that actually the encoding process is actually capturing a lot of details from a model perspective, and…
germayne: Now, how do you actually relate this back to Saturday? Now, back to Saturday, we learned about the retrieval chunks, right? You guys remember that there is, like, a whole sentence?
germayne: then you are basically performing chunking, right? I'm just going to break them down into this, this, this…
germayne: You guys remember, right? Then this is your chunk, so D1, D2… D3… default… D5… and D6.
germayne: And then when you ask a question to the language model, you have the query, right? Q1.
germayne: Correct? So what is it doing behind the scenes? It's actually trying to check the similarity, the cosine similarity, right? If, let's say I have a cosine similarity, cosine similarity.
germayne: I'm actually checking cosine similarity Q1 versus D1.
germayne: D2, D3, D4, I want to take… I want to take the chunks that have similar meaning.
germayne: Correct? That's how the retrieval… Mechanism is done.
germayne: Okay, clear so far?
germayne: So, same thing for image. You have to always encode them to a vector space.
germayne: I hope you guys understand what people talk about when people talk about vector database. So, you know, people always say, oh, vector database. I don't know if you guys heard the term. Who heard the term of vector database before?
germayne: No one heard of it. So I think, I see, I see people shaking your head. So now you know why they call it vector database, right? Because the database is to store vectors.
germayne: Okay, actually, I'm saying something very obvious lah, right?
germayne: vector database is to store vectors. But correct, right? So essentially, if I were to encode everything into vector database, into a vector, then the job of the vector database is, given a query that is also a vector, can I retrieve similar vectors D1?
germayne: Okay?
germayne: And most of the time, they do cosine similarity. I mean, they do a dot product, but it's actually equivalent to cosine similarity, because the embeddings are normalized.
germayne: Okay, I'll stop here first. Anybody has any questions so far, if you're lost?
germayne: Or can follow.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I have a question.
germayne: Yes. Go ahead.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So earlier, right, when we do the… the TFIDF.
germayne: DFID.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I always thought that it's okay to drop all the stop words.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But then I realized, what maybe my documents are all about cancer, and cancer is everywhere in every document. Would he drop the word cancer?
germayne: Cancer is not a stop word, lah. Cancer won't be a stop word. Stop word! Stopword is usually, like, the D's…
germayne: I…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh… what I meant is, like, if…
germayne: They see, they see the wood.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: cancer appears in all the documents. Will you drop it?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because it's very important, right? I mean, that's what I'm doing on one topic or project on cancer. Every document I have is cancer. Cancer is all over the place. In one paragraph, maybe many, many words on cancer. So how… will they drop it?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, like, I just realized this only when you talk, when you discuss, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Would he drop all this… I mean, I agree with dropping sob words.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But what happens in Sunday, the words that is dropped by is actually the… the important word, the one that I'm very concerned with.
germayne: Good, good question, good question, good question. Then maybe I want to ask everyone, what do you guys think? So what's the intuition?
germayne: So if, let's say, you do medical books, do you think that work will be dropped out?
Zac Ang: No.
germayne: Why?
Zac Ang: Cancer is not a stalkboard, and TDF, IDF only makes it, lower or zero.
Zac Ang: It doesn't drop it entirely, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, is it? Okay.
Zac Ang: What, why?
germayne: So, Zach, what's the intuition? Why do you think that cancer, for example, in this example, cancer? Okay, it's a very dark term lah, let's use something different.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So let's say that. They were just kidding in my mind.
germayne: Let's say, like, doctor, let's say, like, medical, medical, let's just say medical, right? Let's say you do something on medical books, then you have the word medical. Why do you think medical will not actually be affected so much? What's the intuition? I mean, every medical book would use the word medical, right? But why? Why do you think it won't be affected too much?
germayne: Why?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Hmm.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Because the proportion of stop words is larger than the word medical or doctor.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: In the first place.
germayne: Correct, so the stop word is going to be much more, right? Like, things like, you know, A, like, it's going to appear a lot of times more, right? Like, the…
germayne: These are actually going to appear much more compared to your, your, your other words.
germayne: These guys are obviously just going to appear much heavier.
germayne: Compared to your medical work.
germayne: So it wouldn't… it wouldn't… in terms of the relativity of importance, it wouldn't… it wouldn't be washed out by these guys.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: But obviously, obviously, obviously, lexical has its own problem. You won't be able to get the meaning, because you're looking at word matches.
germayne: Right, so in practice, I think somebody already said, right, in practice, you do a hybrid.
germayne: in practice.
germayne: Okay? It's an art on how to do it, but in practice, you want to consider both lexical and semantics.
Zac Ang: I have a question.
germayne: Yes.
Zac Ang: So is cosine similarity also the way that,
Zac Ang: grammar or spell check is done. Like, if I spell wrongly, this is how it works to detect what I might mean.
germayne: Mmm…
Zac Ang: Because, like, maybe I spell cat or dog wrongly, and I spell similar wrongly, or something like that.
germayne: Depends, depends, depends on how they formulate. I mean, I don't know, I don't know how… what's the backend algorithm, but it can be formulated as such.
germayne: It can be formulated. So let's say, for example, they might want to retrieve
germayne: words that are similar. Then, cosine sim… okay, so basically, the point here is that cosine similarity basically allows you to measure other vectors that are similar. So if, let's say, they formulate their solution as such, then yes, they will use cosine similarity.
germayne: It depends, it depends. Depends on how they formulate, because just like what I mentioned earlier on, I think Philippe asked the question, can I do this? Depends on your solution. So, recommender, you can also find… you can also
germayne: formulate it in a way where you are retrieving candidates. I mean, it's simple, right?
germayne: So let me, let me put it in a different way.
germayne: So, Zach, so your question can also be that, okay, you know when Netflix shows me all the shows, you know, you know Netflix, you guys, if you guys think about Netflix, right? They sometimes have, like, the, you know, you may like.
germayne: You may like this, this… Y-you- you guys?
germayne: You guys remember? So then the question here, you guys may ask me, hey, then are they using cosine similarity here?
germayne: The answer is, I think it depends.
germayne: Can you do cosine similarity for this? Can you?
germayne: So let's say, for example, I know everybody watch.
germayne: A, B, and C, and then let's say you… let's say, Zach, you like D a lot.
germayne: Can I… can I use a model to say that, okay, let me find all the embeddings that are similar between A, B, and C, and D, and then I retrieve them? Can I do that or not?
germayne: Yes. Ken, right? I can, but then, is that the only way to do that?
germayne: No, right? There are many ways to do that. So, I think to answer your question, unless I work in that company.
germayne: I cannot tell you whether that's how they do it, but if, let's say, they formulate it as such, maybe, let's say, in your spelling, they are able to say that, okay, maybe based on their data.
germayne: All of these words.
germayne: Okay, sorry, so for spelling…
Zac Ang: Like, spell check, is this how it works?
germayne: Maybe not? Maybe not. Okay, maybe, let's say, if they formulate it in a way where they are able to train some kind of vectors where all of these words are commonly spelled wrongly.
germayne: then maybe the retriever might work, but I do not know. But it can be… it can be done like that.
germayne: I hope you get the gist of what I'm saying.
Zac Ang: Yep, okay.
germayne: Yeah, okay.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: But for Netflix, it's… generally, there's a movie database, there's genre and things like that, that will influence it a lot more differently, yeah.
germayne: Yeah, but there are many mechanisms in retrieval. So we're talking about retrieval, right? Like, for the retrieval perspective, there are many algorithms that can do this.
germayne: You can… you can build…
germayne: similarity in terms of genre, in terms of other features, and then you take embedding, you can do that. You can have a model that… they call this two-tower neural network, you can also do that. So, based on my point is that I don't know, I do not know unless
germayne: I know specifically what they do. And I think, famously, back then, they actually created this alternating least square. Okay, I mean, you see, I'm just giving out random…
germayne: So they got this ALS. So you can go and read up on it. I think this is very long ago, alternating lead squared. They use it to predict the matrix.
germayne: in order to perform the recommendation, we can do a dot product. So, I mean, there's many mechanisms, so I don't really… I cannot say, like, what they are using today. But the point here is that all of these are fairly answers. You can do it, do it.
germayne: Because the… the idea here is that if I can always… hey, so now you see, right? Today, you have… you have a data X, X of i.
germayne: You have already learned that I can convert it to some kind of vector, right?
germayne: The takeaway here is you notice, this conversion, This conversion is not universal.
germayne: You can design how you want to convert.
germayne: X to this vector.
germayne: Right? In the neural network, you guys saw that it's like a Lego block. I can design any design I want.
germayne: I can intentionally design, you know, I can say that, let's say let's say in that example.
germayne: I can say that this is a… this is a human.
germayne: I can put the dog, right?
germayne: if I put… if I intentionally say that this is label 1,
germayne: I can train a model where the embedding of this and this will be close together, so that when you do the dot product, they'll be similar. I can define that!
germayne: Because, again, the target label is what you define.
germayne: Right? You can do it in an unsupervised manner. Unsupervised in the sense of, like, it's still supervised, but you are creating a loss function that says that
germayne: If these two are similar, I'm going to make sure that their dog product is going to be very big.
germayne: Okay, sorry, I think this color sucks. So, I'm going to say that, okay, if I want these two to be similar, their dog product will be very big. You can do that to train, and what will happen in the embedding? The embedding will now say that the vector of the human and the dog will be closed.
germayne: So what I'm telling you is there's no right or wrong answer. You, as a user, you define what is the loss, you define what is the target label, and the model will just output for you. That's my point.
germayne: Got it, huh?
germayne: Now, universally, obviously, for language.
germayne: Obviously, what you expect is apple and banana should be closed. This is the expectation, because they are fruits, right?
germayne: Correct? But all I'm telling you is that…
germayne: you can influence the training. You guys notice, right, in the neural network.
germayne: I never define… you can define whatever you want. As long as gradient descent can…
germayne: Update the weights, it will always happen.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, all good? All good, then we will see the example of TF-IDF. This is actually quite, quite straightforward. You will see exactly what was thought.
germayne: Okay, then we'll go to the last part.
germayne: Okay, need, need, need toilet break, or can, can go on.
germayne: Okay, can go on. Okay, then I'll hand over to Sun.
Soon | NTU: In Egglford, or every…
germayne: Okay, okay, okay.
germayne: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Give me a minute, yeah, give me a minute.
germayne: Okay, okay, then I'll entertain you guys, I'll entertain you guys. Okay, any question? Any question? Okay, so I think what I'll tell you guys, I'll just probably entertain you guys.
germayne: So, you see, I got a lot of, like, feeler, right?
germayne: To entertain. Okay, so on Saturday, right, what will happen is I will… I will do a final mind map.
germayne: what I'll do is I will connect. I won't prepare.
germayne: Okay, to make it a bit more challenging for me, I won't prepare anything. What we'll do is we'll do from topic 1, I want you guys to remind me every concept that we have learned from 3.1 all the way to 3.10. Then what we'll do is we'll build the mind map on the spot.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So I'll do it live, and then we will… you guys will tell me what are the topics that we learn. So we'll do that on Saturday. Then on Saturday, we will also give another award. So there'll be another award at the end of the…
germayne: At the end of the class.
germayne: So there'll be some awards to be given.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: And… yeah, and I think we can just take some questions, so just free for all. I think some of you guys maybe will want to ask me more about, like, career, about, about your project, about life.
germayne: You can ask me anything on Saturday, okay? We'll have some time for that.
germayne: Oh, okay, so, so, okay, so Sony's, Sony's back.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let's, go to this section on the, language modeling.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Right, so we have, seen how we need to pre-process the, our language data, right, using, a lot of, stemming, lammatization, and so on, okay? So, just to prepare our
Soon | NTU: Language data, okay, for the next stage.
Soon | NTU: Of the, so-called,
Soon | NTU: the machine learning, the training, the model training, okay? Now, some of the techniques that we need to, let's say, be aware of, is.
Soon | NTU: We have already, seen, like Jermaine had already shared with us, is the engram
Soon | NTU: Right? And also the backwards, right? As well as the TFIDF, right? So these are techniques that allow us to do… transform our data, okay, so that the… the model is able to make use of this technique and then do some kind of,
Soon | NTU: Depending on the use case, so…
Soon | NTU: It can be for predicting the next word, okay? Which, and also some other, applications, okay? So now, for this
Soon | NTU: Nick's, Language modeling techniques that we have,
Soon | NTU: put in in the notebook, right, is the bigram. Okay, bigram, as you can… as the name suggests, right, in one, so-called, all the tokens, okay, basically, we are getting all the token
Soon | NTU: Pero.
Soon | NTU: Right? With, each other. Of course, there's some kind of, overlap, okay? So to do that, we'll see how that bigram works, right? So, we will import the…
Soon | NTU: necessary library from the NLTK, and also this, collection, package, okay? So, what, this is…
Soon | NTU: doing is, of course, there are some other, variations, okay? Trigram also available, and also, unigram, okay, so if you can
Soon | NTU: have time to try it out, okay? By all means. So instead of two, Trigram will make it 3.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And so on. Okay, so… Nope.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so in this case, we are going to use a 5 gram…
Soon | NTU: to do the, language modeling. So, Tango is to…
Soon | NTU: Do some, so-called count the number of, Oh.
Soon | NTU: The word path, the bigram, within the vocabulary, okay?
Soon | NTU: And also… We have some kind of a default dictionary to format your token in the
Soon | NTU: copper way. Now, so we have this corpus
Soon | NTU: So, very simple, oversimplified, but it's sufficient to, for us to see, you know, the concept of the piegram, okay? So, because there is a…
Soon | NTU: repeating group.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the rest are quite unique, right? And then, let's see… How the bigram works, okay?
Soon | NTU: So now, the next step is we're going to tokenize the corpus, which is just one statement like this, right? And then, of course, you can, along the way, you know, take a look at what each of the variables
Soon | NTU: Looks like, right, you always have tried to do that to help you understand better the logic of your codes in the notebook, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: Right? So basically, the first step is always to tokenize your corpus. Okay, so in this case, it's only one sentence, right? And as you can see, we also include some punctuation in our tokens, okay? How about this?
Soon | NTU: Bye, Graham What you can do to help us
Soon | NTU: Right? To do the language modeling. So let's see what it can do, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: Right? You will pair up all this token, I am.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and based on this counter,
Soon | NTU: Method, okay, so it is able to tell us, oh, they're actually Occurrence of the… A…
Soon | NTU: I am paired within this corpus.
Soon | NTU: Okay? The rest are only a copy. Okay, so as you can see, I am… I'm Sam.
Soon | NTU: Then, Sam, Pustel.
Soon | NTU: push stop, SAM, and so on, okay? So all the tokens are paired up.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that will help the…
Soon | NTU: If we are using bigram, right, so that will help the language model later, after training, to predict, right? In my word is, I'm to start off with, right, what should be the next word?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so in this case, very likely that is.
Soon | NTU: M.
Soon | NTU: Okay? He goes… This one occurred two times.
Soon | NTU: So it has a very high probability attached to the diagram, okay? So let's continue. Now.
Soon | NTU: So we're going to sum up this bigram to see how many, because we need to compute the, probability just for this corpus. So imagine in the…
Soon | NTU: Let's say the actual real estate, and we may have a lot of Just more than 16.
Soon | NTU: Migraine, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, it could be… 100,000, and even more, okay, for our… modeling. Now, so this…
Soon | NTU: Come up to be about 16 of them.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then… From that, we will compute the probability of each of the migrants. Okay, so you can also…
Soon | NTU: You know what I mean, prenup.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, there is a probability associated to it, each of the vibrant.
Soon | NTU: And then, there's also a similar information here. Okay, so, as you can see.
Soon | NTU: So, 2 over 16 is about 0.125.
Soon | NTU: So the rest is, 1 over 16.
Soon | NTU: All having the same probability. Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: So this is, one good example to show how we can use Biogram to help the
Soon | NTU: Language model to learn, again, what… how to predict the next word.
Soon | NTU: Given, work like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but of course, if it is given a word like, let's say, Sam, or some other…
Soon | NTU: words not appearing here, okay, so probably you will not get the, very accurate and meaningful prediction, right? Okay, because our corpus are only trained with just a limited number of, tokens.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, so in this case, like, there's a lot of 0.6.0625, so you always, you will choose, what?
Soon | NTU: Could be wrong.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, whoa, what did you?
Soon | NTU: So this is an oversimplified, so-called a sample
Soon | NTU: Okay, example. Okay, so in actual… Fino, maybe you have, not likely to have
Soon | NTU: By gram with the same probability.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you can choose another example to try it out, you know?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, in this case, this toy example, the probability is useless,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Right.
Soon | NTU: It's useless in this case, because they're all the same.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, they're all the same, huh?
Soon | NTU: Yeah, if you can provide maybe a better example, for…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Help us, then maybe that will help the machine learning, the model, the language models to learn.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, would the management model pick up the one that has highest probability, or the lower one?
Soon | NTU: Depending on what you provide, lah, as a first one.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, okay.
Soon | NTU: Yeah.
Soon | NTU: Because, if you say, not… not likely that you will…
Soon | NTU: Okay, probably you will just… because everything's the same, so if you say the starting word is not lah, then likely it will give you the, like, lah.
Soon | NTU: Not late.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay. I'll try to understand how to read this, this, out, this.
Soon | NTU: It's really all worth to be fine, so-called the.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, let's say, let's it, let's say, let's say the first one, IM. So… so if I… if… so, is it, like, he sees the I, then you'll… you'll give the M, or… or… I don't know.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, correct.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Is that how I should read this?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I'll pour…
Soon | NTU: this gift.
Soon | NTU: This is how this, circle you build up to train your language model, okay?
Soon | NTU: This is a capability lah, okay?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, so you train it lah, so you see the first word, then what's the next word, you see this word, then what's the next word? That's how I should read the output lah.
Soon | NTU: Right, right.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I won't keep it on.
Soon | NTU: the garden left.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I don't know how you read the thing, it's like…
Soon | NTU: Language model, you know, yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, so you see, Hamlet, make a full stop. Oh, okay, okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so next, we will go through this, KFIBF, right? So…
Soon | NTU: Charmaine has already shared, right, how we actually compute this, using this formula, the…
Soon | NTU: Importance of a word to a document, and also compare it How is this word?
Soon | NTU: relevant or important in the collection of corpus, okay? So, this formula, will… Got your son.
Soon | NTU: Let me see whether that word is,
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you have stock words, right, what do you expect the value of the TF IPM? Is it to be very high or low?
Soon | NTU: For some worse.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Noah.
Soon | NTU: Lower. Say lower, yeah, yeah. Okay, so stop words, likely that you…
Soon | NTU: Have a very high value in the numerator.
Soon | NTU: Okay? As well as in the denominator.
Soon | NTU: being sold.
Soon | NTU: low, Okay, so you have,
Soon | NTU: A high number here will likely make the whole thing very low, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so how about… Keywords.
Soon | NTU: Keywords likely to be high, right?
Soon | NTU: Right? Okay, so that is, how we can make use of TF-ITF to do the, so-called evaluate the importance of a word in a document, and as well as across the corpus, okay? Of course, there are some limitations, stated here, right? No,
Soon | NTU: can depend.
Soon | NTU: dependency, right?
Soon | NTU: So, as well as the no semantic relationship.
Soon | NTU: Captured, and also the,
Soon | NTU: sparse vectors, and high dimension, okay? So we have a… again, another oversimplified example, okay, of a corpus, just to illustrate the concept of a TF-IDF, as well as
Soon | NTU: a cosine similarity to compare whether this document
Soon | NTU: is similar to another document. Okay, so we have a list of documents here. So, one sentence is equivalent to one document.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now we have four documents. Just imagine that this is a document about blue sky, second one is about bright sun.
Soon | NTU: the document is about sun, sky, both upright, right? And also, The last document is about…
Soon | NTU: someone seeing Shining sun, and shining and bright sun.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we were first… call this TFIDF vector. Okay, so we were going to vectorize.
Soon | NTU: Okay? The words… In this, corpus, King.
Soon | NTU: And then… We do a training.
Soon | NTU: So this vector will go into this document, okay, basically it contains only 4 lines, and then create, what we call the TF IDN matrix, okay? So the…
Soon | NTU: Metrics look like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, as you can see, This corpus, right?
Soon | NTU: has, how, how many… Vocabulary are there in this corpus?
Soon | NTU: The corpus of a fall document.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so as you can count, we get 1, 2, 3, 4… Fine. 6.
Soon | NTU: 7… 8, 9… 10… 11.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, don't count the punctuation, okay? So, there are 11… So-called the worst.
Soon | NTU: token inside this vocabulary. You don't repeatedly count, because it must be a unique word, okay? So, 11 words.
Soon | NTU: And using that 11 words, right, you will form a vector, okay, attach a number for each of the words, okay? So, as you can see.
Soon | NTU: Here, right?
Soon | NTU: Ying.
Soon | NTU: I have.
Soon | NTU: Okay, if you can count, right, there are actually 11 unique numbers, they're because this corpus have
Soon | NTU: the… the… the… here, right? Some repetition in some of the words, okay? So, this is actually equivalent to your corpus here, but it's in vector form, means in number form, okay? So, each vector has a dimension of
Soon | NTU: How many?
Soon | NTU: How many elements per… Erie.
Soon | NTU: Oh, sorry, per lease?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: What do you count 11? I don't… Oh, you mean the ish, each square brackets,
Soon | NTU: Yes, okay, so because there are four documents, right, so there will be four.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, before squares, four…
Soon | NTU: Element, we have, 11 numbers.
Soon | NTU: One number for each.
Soon | NTU: What kept my… there's a vocab size.
Soon | NTU: We'll get you the poem.
Soon | NTU: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Soon | NTU: 7, 8, 9, 10.
Soon | NTU: 11.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, of course, each of the words is converted into a number, okay? But if you're going to bring this, relate back to the original, okay? So, as you can see, the is having a value of 0.659,
Soon | NTU: And then this one is occupied by N, some other word which is not here, okay? So sky is,
Soon | NTU: Somewhere here.
Soon | NTU: Agreed.
Soon | NTU: But you, you really have to get the, the original, vocab, right?
Soon | NTU: In order to map.
Soon | NTU: Get back the words based on the number here.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Now, when you apply the quasi-similarity, right, on the metrics, right, you know.
Soon | NTU: When we deal with this kind of a function, to compare with two documents, we basically need to compare
Soon | NTU: In numbers, right? We cannot compare text.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Right? Because in a vector space, everything have to be represented by numbers, okay? Now, using this cosine similarity.
Soon | NTU: Now, this example is… Showing you weather.
Soon | NTU: TF IDMatrix 1 is the second document, okay? So, we are comparing
Soon | NTU: The second document versus the other first document.
Soon | NTU: Including itself.
Soon | NTU: And then, third document, fourth document, again. And then this is the…
Soon | NTU: So-called a lease of, value.
Soon | NTU: That represent the similarity between Document… second document versus document one.
Soon | NTU: Second, Tokimo versus itself is usually one, right? Versus itself is usually
Soon | NTU: Very… it's usually one, which is…
Soon | NTU: Meaning the same. But when you compare to third document, there is a very, the content looks… seem to be very similar.
Soon | NTU: Compared to Document 1 and Document…
Soon | NTU: As you can see from the…
Soon | NTU: so-called the value, which is a measure of the similarity, okay? The higher the value.
Soon | NTU: The higher the similarity between two documents.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So why, why is this so… So low for the opponent.
Soon | NTU: 364, Document 1.
Soon | NTU: Are we able to know the token list for mapping?
Soon | NTU: in the TF IDX factor, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let's see… They are…
Soon | NTU: Oops.
Soon | NTU: We have,
Soon | NTU: Sorry, I need to… We won't
Soon | NTU: There should be a function for…
Soon | NTU: tagging each of the numbers, right, you can derive from here, okay? Really?
Soon | NTU: Okay, Adrian.
Soon | NTU: But the original words are here, because in the later part of the quotes, right, we actually removed the stop words.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: just to see… How this, similarity, the…
Soon | NTU: numbers, right, can be improved or increased, okay? Because without the stop words, right, your similarity, check using cosine, similarity will be,
Soon | NTU: will be higher.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now we have 0.36.
Soon | NTU: 1, 0.7254, 0.54, okay? Now, we are going to remove the stop words in this TF-IDF vector metrics, right?
Soon | NTU: So this is what… We need to do…
Soon | NTU: Right? By specifying the stop weight, if you do not specify, the default is none.
Soon | NTU: Right? The default is none. Okay, so we are telling the vectorizer to remove any stock word in English, okay? So, as you can see, we will have,
Soon | NTU: Shorter, vocabulary list, right?
Soon | NTU: Good.
Soon | NTU: Okay, only 5 words remains in the vocabulary, okay? So, if you're going to check the similarity score, you'll notice that, you know, it is able to even increase this and tell you, oh.
Soon | NTU: Document 2 versus Document 1 are totally different content, even topic, right? Whereas it has a quite similar content, right? We are talking about sun, right?
Soon | NTU: So, versus the document 3 and 4.
Soon | NTU: They, indeed, are also talking about the sun.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is,
Soon | NTU: how we use, cosine similarity, with and without removing the stockwards again. You can now see the difference
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… thingy has, okay, let's try to… Print out this.
Soon | NTU: There must be a function to associate each of the numbers to the vocabulary.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that is, part 2 of the, no, boom.
Soon | NTU: Session.
Soon | NTU: The third part will be about invading lah. Okay, so,
Soon | NTU: Any, any question, from anyone?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Can you… can you let me see what you typed earlier?
Soon | NTU: What do you want to look at, Noel?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: This one, this one, just, this one, this number 5.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I think so, I, I, I didn't… Is it green?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Where are you being twice at?
Soon | NTU: Employees different. Sorry.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: When's it on?
Soon | NTU: Technically. Okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Once I got error, I wasn't glad I typed wrongly.
Soon | NTU: Right? Okay, so no questions, let me hand over to… Germaine?
germayne: Yep, okay, thank you.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: This is why they said output.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: 0…
germayne: Okay, so I think we were… we are now at the last part.
germayne: Okay, I think before I continue, just want to clarify one thing. I think just now Noelle was asking about the medical thing, right? So, I think on second thought, I think what I said is not exactly correct. So, if let's say, hypothetically.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But it's not correct.
germayne: Okay, so let's go back to that same question that was asked. So you say that, okay, let's say you have medical books, and you put all the medical books together, then the term medical will be penalized, correct?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Based on the TI idea, it would be taken out more, right?
germayne: Correct, correct. But then the idea here, I think, is that if medical is taken out, then medical must be a word that is not important to differentiate the documents, correct?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, Correo.
germayne: So, so then it's, like, a bit like, let's say, if I have a feature in your Visio flat, and all of it is, like, the same, then it must be useless.
germayne: to partition the data, correct, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, yeah, alright.
germayne: a useful input must be one that is able to partition the different instances, correct?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But in this case, in the document, it might be an important word to know, right?
germayne: No, no, it won't be important, because let's say in the case of your medical book, right, then the term medical will not be important, but let's say something like all the different diseases, those will be unique across the book, right? Yeah, then those terms will be more important. So medical would be a bad term in this case. It's not important for us to have any meaning.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Thank you for.
germayne: between the documents, so I think that should be the intuition.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay. Okay, okay, anyway,
germayne: Okay, so I think you guys seen the TF-IDF vectorizer, I think we'll just go to the last part.
germayne: So the… obviously, the last part now is that the… and again, not surprising, we talk about this the whole time, is that actually we can use
germayne: models that has been pre-trained, right, on other objectives, and they actually can encode the input
germayne: text data into embeddings, right? So you can see in this example.
germayne: We are able to convert all of these different words into embeddings, and the literature here is actually basically telling us that the expected embeddings distance
germayne: right, the cosine similarity, we should expect them to be very similar, okay? Obviously, in the neural network perspective, we will just do a dot product.
germayne: But like what I mentioned, if you were to do a dot product, basically a dot product.
germayne: You… if… and if you normalize the embeddings, these will be equal, so normalized embeddings.
germayne: Right? You normalize it by its unit vector. If you normalize it, you take the dot product, it's actually equal… equivalent to cosine similarity.
germayne: Okay? So the idea here is that the embeddings you should expect
germayne: You know, the semantic meaning to be closer, and that is the difference between
germayne: TFIDF, convectorizer, as compared to using a neural network.
germayne: Okay, and of course, these neural network has been pre-trained on each of the separate tasks.
germayne: Okay, so again, the idea here is that because they are… they are pre-trained, which means that they have already… they were actually already trained on large number of corpuses or text data.
germayne: then actually somehow the semantic meaning is actually captured, right? It's actually able to know that happy and joyful, for example, you can see that even though if we look at the lexical match, it doesn't match at all, but semantically, they should be close in the vector space. And probably this is because it's able to see
germayne: You know, again, why this happened, not very sure, but when we train all of these models, it's actually based on the fact that either they are predicting
germayne: The next word?
germayne: Or they are just predicting some of the fill-in-the-blanks, right?
germayne: In terms of the data set. So the target label usually is formulated in a way that they are actually doing mass language modeling, or some form, and somehow from here, we're actually able to get
germayne: These meanings from
germayne: The tokens that has been similar semantically, to be… to be actually similar if you were to plot them in the vector space.
germayne: Right? So what this means is that then now you can actually apply all your algorithms, like clustering, you can do whatever, and you can even put them into traditional machine learning models, okay? So typically what people do is that if, let's say.
germayne: you have your… so, wait, so here, so here's the context, right? So, in typical models, because now you are able to have
germayne: You're able to convert, so let's say you have some pre-trained model.
germayne: retrained model. Let me zoom in a bit more.
germayne: So if, let's say, you have some pre-trained model, you can convert your X data your X data.
germayne: You basically can convert them into some kind of semantics.
germayne: vector. You can actually directly use this semantics vector as features into your traditional machine learning model.
germayne: Right? Which you guys are exposed to. So things like your XGBoost, your Cat Boost, and your, you know, LightGBM, actually is still relevant. Right? Because the idea here is that these features
germayne: These features here.
germayne: that has been converted actually captured the semantics meaning. So it's not necessarily… and usually here is a neural network. Usually this is a neural network, right? Usually for the pre-trained model here. So it's actually a very, very common workflow to…
germayne: convert semantics, and you can also add in lexical features. You can still do feature engineering on all the text matches, and usually you can put them into machine learning models.
germayne: Okay, so that's a very common workflow, right? And you can do classification or whatever, okay? So, example, maybe, let's say…
germayne: you know, let's say in the example of your VCO flat prices, your VCO flat prediction, you can, in fact, explore, you know, if there are some description about the flat, right? I think you guys were mentioning, like, oh, you know, maybe next step I can use
germayne: I can use, like, the quality of the flat in order to put as features. You can actually use things like the review data.
germayne: Right, you can use certain description, right, to capture the semantics meaning, and you can put them as features in your model. Okay, that's one example.
germayne: Okay, I'm not going to show this, you guys can watch this on your own. Okay, so, as I mentioned, most of the time, the embedding models are actually neural networks, so these are just some famous ones, so just some famous example. No, I'm not going to talk specifically about, like, Glov and FastX, but essentially, this… these three were, like, the older…
germayne: older models, based on the old neural network architecture, but it's based on the transformer architecture. So you notice one thing here, that it says that the embedding type is static, static, static, while it's contextual. So I'll take a bit of time to describe this, right? It might not make sense for everyone today.
germayne: Because you… you don't really understand the… the…
germayne: attention layer first. But essentially, from a neural network perspective, we didn't really teach this, but when you do neural network, it's actually very common. So if you remember, neural networks, we have the… their different layers. We thought some of the layers where, you know, you have the linear layers.
germayne: Again, linear is basically your W, right? Your W for that specific block. And you can basically stack all the different blocks together. Thursday, we will learn a more advanced version of, like, all the different architectures. But essentially, there's one more layer that we didn't talk about. It's actually called the embedding layer. So this is called the embedding layer.
germayne: So what the embedding layer does is that you get to define, two things, right, in the embedding layer. You get to define the number of… the size of the embedding layer, and usually in the case of NLP, it's actually the vocab size.
germayne: So this is the vocab size, which means the total number of unique vocab. And in the second thing, you actually define the hidden dimension.
germayne: So this is basically the embedding layer. And what the embedding layer does is that if you think about it, vocab and hidden dimension is that it's actually like a lookup table.
germayne: So, on… on this side, it's gonna be V,
germayne: Where V is the total number of vocabulary size. So if your vocab size is 1 million, then essentially where 1 million rows, the matrix will be V size, and the axis here will be the hidden dimension.
germayne: Right? So essentially, you have a V by, V by D matrix, and why this is a lookup table is actually very simple. So each row, if you think about it, is going to be a representation of the vocab.
germayne: in B dimension, right? So you can see, yeah, these are the vocab. So let's say, for example, boy, let's say boy.
germayne: Boy will be a specific role.
germayne: Where it's a 1 by D dimension.
germayne: So what this means is that, actually, when you train your neural network, these embedding layers will get updated, which means that the representation of each of these vectors, or each of your vocab, will be represented by D-dimension.
germayne: And in all of these older models, essentially, they use this fixed dimension. So after you train the model, essentially, you would… you would just take out the… the V by D. So if, let's say, you have a sentence, I am…
germayne: a boy.
germayne: So basically, 1, 2, 3, 4. So let's say if this is the raw tokens, right, again, I'm simplifying this. If this is the raw tokens, 1, 2, 3, 4, so you have a 4 by D dimension vector.
germayne: Right? And then you can aggregate these in order to represent the entire sentence. But the idea here is that you notice that this is fixed.
germayne: Okay, so if you were to change the sequence of these words, if let's say I… Boy.
germayne: Can I ask you guys, if I were to change the sequence, does the… does the… does the top…
germayne: Does the total 4 by D vector changes?
germayne: it doesn't change, because I'm just looking out from this table, right, V by D.
germayne: Okay? So that's what it means by the contextual here is standard. The embedding type is standard. Now, for attention, right, you guys won't understand, but attention mechanism, right, I am a boy.
germayne: Attention, basically, what the word means is that you will… we'll talk a bit deeper about this on Thursday, but attention basically means that they have something called the self-attention. So, I'm able to know, with respect to itself, I, right, with respect to M, a boy, I'm able to know the context based on the width. So, it's able to know this thing called attention. So.
germayne: If boy is actually a very big context, I am a boy.
germayne: you can imagine that boy has a very strong contact, so the weight of boy is going to be very high. And what it does is that it's going to take a weighted sum, a weighted sum of all of these, right? It's going to take the… basically this call, they call this the…
germayne: the key value, the key value pair. But essentially, when we calculate the… using the key and the value, we can calculate a weighted sum of all the attention with respect to the words. And because of that, right, if the word context were to change, the resulting embeddings would be different.
germayne: Okay? It also uses the V by D…
germayne: embedding layer, but because in the attention layer, the attention hill calculated would be different. So that means that if your sentence were to change the ordering.
germayne: contextually, if it's different, the output will be slightly different, which means that the embedding type is not static, it's actually contextual. That actually is one reason why attention models are very, very powerful for sequence-based data, okay? Which is why it's the state of the art today.
germayne: Okay? All your large language models are powered by some level of attention, right? Which is basically the transformer architecture, okay? And you can see that the dimension is typically 768, and then you have the 1024. It's a very standard size.
germayne: Okay, so with that said, I think you guys will just see a very simple example that you can basically use this, all this model to predict, to perform inference on the output, right? But usually, we would… usually for embeddings, we use what is called the… the encoder. So basically, we use… we use the… we use the encoder, usually the encoder.
germayne: Because we want to encode.
germayne: the data into some kind of representation of N by D.
germayne: Right? If, let's say, your… sorry, if let's say, your sentence is N by 1, we will encode it to N by D, right? In your large language model, right, the one where you're always predicting the next word, usually that's the… that's the decoding part.
germayne: the decoder. So we're not talking about that, we're talking about the encoder portion, okay, which you will see later on. I'm not sure whether if the notebook has the bird example, but you can essentially use all this model to convert any of your text data into embedding representation, which are very, very powerful.
germayne: Okay? Anybody has any questions here? I'm going a bit fast on the transformer, because we'll talk about it on…
germayne: Thursday, but even if I go through on Thursday, you might not understand, but I'll give you the material, so that you go through the math in your own free time to understand it. Okay? Go through the math, and you'll understand what I mean by the key. So basically, they got a Q, K, V, basically the query key and value.
germayne: Right? And you can basically calculate
germayne: the… the… the attention, and you can… yeah, but that's not the point. The point here is to just tell you guys why is it that BERT is contextual in this case, right?
germayne: Anybody has any questions so far, for me?
germayne: Oh, IC got a few things.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, going back to… okay, sorry, I'm probably digressing a bit. Yeah. So, earlier we talked about, like, my medical and cancer thing, right? So, earlier we talked about that this, I think Philip, right? Philip was saying that, because there are many other… there are more stop words.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So the… the medical will not,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: will not be canceled. It's wrong, that way of thinking is wrong,
germayne: Okay, in that hypothetically simple example, right, if let's say your document only got 5, and then 5 of them have medical, then from that formula standpoint, you can notice that the medical will not be able to be differentiated from the stop words.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, correct.
germayne: So that is correct.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You'll be dropped, lah, it'll be dropped, yeah, it'll be dropped.
germayne: Yes, but…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: The reason is not because… but the reason is not because there are many more stopboards around, that's why this thing is dropped.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay. Or will not be dropped.
germayne: Okay, so there's two points to answer back to that question. Firstly, in scikit-learn, you can define stop words as well, so the stop words will automatically be dropped.
germayne: You can also define that. Number two, if let's say you choose not to do that, and in that simple example, the medical is appearing as frequent as the other stop words, then basically the intuition here is that it is not that important, because it.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: Appreciate the documents.
germayne: But they're not considered stop words lah, I think in a, in a…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Crayola, So it's like, we… because my idea was, like, if we drop lah, I know, it's just that…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: my… my concern is that if it's dropped, then if it's important, then will it be… will it matter? But if it doesn't matter, then, okay, lah, I mean, it's like…
germayne: Okay, but the intuition here is that why you still have the motivation to drop is because it still affects your dimension space.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, correct.
germayne: Right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Block.
germayne: Through dropping them, the vector size will be smaller.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah. Yes. But I cannot… but I cannot say that it will not be dropped, because there are many other stop words around, right? That's why we will…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: That was our initial discussion.
germayne: No, no, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So that one's wrong lah, right?
germayne: Yes, if you look at the formula, yeah, yeah, that's why I corrected. You look at.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: All right.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, yeah.
germayne: It's just total number of documents in Corpus D divided by total number of documents containing term T.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: So if the formula is the same, then the IDF here will be the same. Doesn't know.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Hmm.
germayne: Correct, right? Total number of documents, indeed, divided by total number of… in that hypothetical… of course, it won't be in that case. Of course, that's a very simple example.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: But in that simple example, the argument here is that if term T anyways is appearing many times, then it's not helpful for me to give any meaning, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, I would definitely drop it lah. The other thing is, like, it would drop it that hard. Yeah.
germayne: Okay, yeah, I hope you can… I hope that that answers… yes, Philip, I know you want to ask.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Back to your, just now that formula, if your chunk size, just now you, the lock, the lock one.
germayne: Oh, sorry, you guys keep going back? Okay, okay. Okay, okay, better.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Would the chance size actually…
germayne: Chang size.
germayne: I know.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Chunking.
germayne: I mean, the chunk becomes a document, so if, let's say, if you have chunks, right, the chunks is a document.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Yeah, so the chunking will, in a sense, also determine how good or bad this formula.
germayne: Yes, to some extent, okay? The reason I say yes is because when you think about the retrieval, right, retrieval, usually they don't use TFIDF, they use BM25.
germayne: BM25, the formula is a bit more complex. There is some saturation term, if the term appears too many times, etc, etc. Largely similar to TF-IDF, but for a lot of lexical matches, it uses BM25. Oh, sorry.
germayne: If that's your question, if you talk about chunking. So, the reason why I brought in another thing is because in practice, people don't do TF-IDF on retrieval. Lexical, they use BM25. That is the practice.
germayne: But it's similar, conceptually, it's similar. It's similar where you are doing something like that, where if a term appears many times, and if a term appears many times across document, then I basically know that it's not that important. That word is not that important. So the weight gets shrinked… gets shrinked down.
germayne: But the formula is a bit more complex for BM25. You guys can read up on your own.
germayne: That is in that context of chunking. You're talking about chunking, right?
germayne: But if you want to think about, okay, how does chunking relate to here, then the per document is actually affected by the chunks, because, you know, when we talk about D1, D2, this is actually the chunk that you're talking about.
germayne: If that doesn't confuse you.
germayne: If you know what I'm saying.
germayne: Okay, feel it?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Yep. Okay.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: And…
germayne: I think the idea here is correct lah. If you're trying to ask me, does the chunking affect this BM25 and the ALGO, right? Of course it does lah. If your… if your chunk is very big, right, you contain a lot of documents, then what is captured in that, that the premium document also will change what?
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: But that's for the lexical part lah, yeah.
germayne: Alright.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Thanks.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, anyway, nobody curious about this. Oh, sorry.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I'm just wondering about embeddings, huh?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You mentioned earlier that the neural network also do unveilings,
germayne: Yes, yes, exactly, yes, yes. Embedding layer… okay, just to recap, embedding layer, you are just doing a V by D lookup table. Now, my question to you guys is, can I apply this on things outside of text?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, lookup table.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So you're.
germayne: No, so, so, so can I, can I ask, can I ask you guys?
germayne: if the neural network here, I'm just saying that for embedding layer, it's just a V by D, where it's just a total number of element by dimension. Can I apply that for another use case?
germayne: Yeah, maybe I'll help you guys.
germayne: Let's say I have the resio flat data X.
germayne: I have one variable, caught…
germayne: the type of, the, the type of house, okay? I mean, I don't know if that, that is… that is that. I think there's a, there's a, there's a, there's a variable that is, like, 4-room, 5-room, or… Yeah, flat type.
germayne: Et cetera, et cetera, right? The flat type, right?
germayne: Let's say the unique number of flat type here is 6.
germayne: Can I use the embedding layer to create a 6xD lookup table?
germayne: Can I do that?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I don't see why not.
germayne: Yeah, exactly you can. So the embedding layer doesn't care. Basically, all it does is that if you put in.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But what I don't understand is, where does embedding fit into the neural network? I mean, like, you have the W and the X.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So where does the embedding fit in? I mean, I don't see how is it… is it, like, hidden in the… is one of the hidden layer?
germayne: No, no, no, embedding layer is like another LEGO block.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Family, so it's another… So…
germayne: If, so, so if, let's say, let's say in the example, okay, again, simple example, let's say I got 3 variables here. I got flat type.
germayne: I got the… the square feet.
germayne: square feet.
germayne: And I got the… the VCO price.
germayne: Okay?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: This is your Y data.
germayne: This is your X data.
germayne: Correct?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: In this case, if I have flat type.
germayne: It's a categorical variable, I cannot convert it.
germayne: to text, hypothetically, right? I got 6 of 6 unique value.
germayne: Here, I have N by 1.
germayne: So in your neural network, right, here will be N by 1.
germayne: This is the… so this one, the square feet will come in.
germayne: Usually, this one will be the embedding layer, so this one can come into the embedding layer. So what the embedding layer does is that it will map
germayne: because there's 6 by D lookup table, right? I have 6… I have a D… I have 6 unique values, so what it does is that you will map
germayne: every resilotype value here to D, so here the dimension becomes N by D.
germayne: Correct? Can you see, right? M by 1…
germayne: M by 1 is your X, then if, let's say, you got a W here, right?
germayne: So usually what happens is that you do a CONCAT. Okay, I'm basically confusing you guys.
germayne: the idea here is N by 1 by D, right? Actually, here, before you put into… here, sorry, before… so here…
germayne: you agree that now I have D columns to represent my flat tide.
germayne: I have one column to represent my square feet. Can follow so far? So how many columns do I have?
germayne: What was my… what's my column? How many columns do I… I'll repeat again. You got…
germayne: 2X data, square feet, and your flat type. I put this into embedding layer, embedding layer now gives me N by D. N number of resio flat, D number of representation, because it's a lookup table, right? 6 by D.
germayne: Now, I have the square feet, N by 1.
germayne: In total, how many columns do I have now? And by what?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: And by what? Okay, Teng Li say 2.
germayne: Any article, any answer?
germayne: How many features do I have right now?
germayne: What was this? Is it 2?
germayne: Are you sure?
germayne: No.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I thought 3 years.
germayne: tree?
germayne: What are you guys basically guessing, is it?
Zac Ang: Isn't it 1 plus?
germayne: Exactly, D plus 1.
germayne: Correct? Fantastic.
germayne: Okay, then now…
germayne: go by the W, right? Then, Noel, do you think this will work from whatever we learn?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, oh, so the D plus 1 becomes a weight.
germayne: No, the D plus 1 becomes the feature.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh…
germayne: your weight can… let's say you put 100 units, 1000, 1000. Then this one becomes, what, M by 1,000, right? It doesn't matter.
germayne: Okay, maybe I'm just confusing for you guys. But the important point here is that the embedding layer is just a lookup table, and then people usually use it, right, to map to some kind of representation, therefore it's fixed.
germayne: Therefore, the problem here is you notice that it's fixed by the vocab size.
germayne: So, what this means, right, is that, let's say, for example, if tomorrow you change the vocab to V plus 5,
germayne: Can I use the V plus D or not?
germayne: Are you guys able to understand?
germayne: So the V… then, if let's say I change the vocab to V plus 5, right? But my lookup table only got V, then I need to retrain my model, because the embedding layer is fixed, right?
germayne: So that was the problem for the older ones. Okay, actually, BirdRide also uses that embedding, but I don't want to confuse you guys. But just that Bird, right, because of the way that they tokenize, the vocab size is actually very flexible, so they are not fixed to that fixed vocab size in that sense lah.
Zac Ang: Sorry, does that mean that for Bert.
Zac Ang: V is a big number.
germayne: Okay, so there's some new ones,
germayne: For, usually for the latest
germayne: large language models, right? The vocab, right, they use a different way of encoding the vocab. They use this thing called bytepair.
germayne: So basically, you represent them in terms of this byte pair, which can allow you to express into a very large number of vocab. So it's not like… it's not the words that you're thinking about, it's not like… it's not like I am… it's not like that. They're not looking at it like that. They do… they do this BP, but okay, we… we are… we are digressing, but to answer your question, right.
germayne: the BERT… the BERT model doesn't face this problem, it's because they use a different tokenization method.
germayne: They're not using the… the… the… the tokenization that we discussed, the… the… the… what do you call it? The one that you guys saw in the spaCon. Because, logically, right, if you guys saw the spaCy one, if you do by white space, right, there's so many words to represent. How… how can I… my vocab needs to be very big, agreed?
germayne: If I put them in words. So, byte pair encoding, again, I do not know whether all the closed source model uses, but byte pair encoding is one mechanism where they actually reduce it to a very small, common byte pair.
germayne: Which allows you to express in a larger number of vocab words.
germayne: Okay, that's out of today's topic, out of… you have to go and explore that on your own.
germayne: The only thing here is that the embedding type is contextual because of the attention layer. The reason here is contextual is because whenever we do a forward propagation, it calculates the attention. The attention changes depending on the words that's surrounding the
germayne: tokens.
germayne: and for encoding, they do something called bidirection. Okay, here, I'm basically confusing, guys, because there's actually a very, very deep concept, just like what Briar just mentioned. It's actually very deep, so…
germayne: For the encoding, they do this bi-direction attention, which actually affects the output of the width. So therefore, the embedding type is slightly different. But in all of these older models, right, the embedding comes directly from the embedding layer. Bird also has an embedding layer, but just that we don't use the embedding layer. We use the attention's output.
germayne: the encoded form.
germayne: Just need to know that Bird is stronger, okay? Bird is, like, state of the art today.
germayne: For capturing and coding.
germayne: Okay, if not, if not, whatever I say, I think you guys just repeat the video lah.
germayne: I think when you revise.
Zac Ang: Sorry, RITOV here means out of vocabulary.
germayne: Yes, yes. Out of vocabulary, yes. But just like what I mentioned, for bird, right, they can handle out our vocab is because their vocab is tokenized in a different way, so it's not exactly by the word.
germayne: So it can actually represent a large number of representation.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: My understanding of embedding is, like, it's like, you have something, then you put something into it.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So that, you can, you know, you can, like, do something better.
germayne: Okay, it's a, it's a, it's.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Is it the same way? Is this ideal?
germayne: can do something better, mmm…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Or to help you with certain activity lah, because that's how you embed something, mah.
germayne: Okay, so the.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: That's what I… that's what I'm thinking about. Is it the same idea?
germayne: Yeah, so today we learn X, we convert to vector.
germayne: This thing is called a vector.
germayne: This thing is also called an embedding.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: And the story behind is because of this. It's because of… it's because of this, this.
germayne: Because of this. Because historically, right, when people put it into the neural network, people take the vectors out from the embedding layer, so I think they call it the embedding.
germayne: There's just… it's all single name lah, but basically, to convert some kind of unstructured data here can be image.
germayne: Here can be your tags.
germayne: But essentially, when we perform some inference, we convert them to vector space, we usually call them the embedings.
germayne: Usually from a neural network model.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: Got it?
germayne: So they are just… the people just…
germayne: people just change the name on the fly. So when people say, oh, hey, I want to get the embeddings, usually it's from the model, perform inference on it, and you just basically get the representation of the original data in vector space. That is the embedding. So this thing is the embedding, this one.
germayne: Make sense?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: Yeah, just a representation.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: This for neural networks, neural networks you're.
germayne: Yes, usually, usually people use it as an output of neural networks, usually.
germayne: You don't put a… you don't put a TF IDF and then call it embeddings. I don't think people call it that way, yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Wow, very interesting, huh?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Two… two turns for the same thing.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Which depends on where you use it. But anyway…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You start using.
germayne: but they are… but mathematically, they are just a… they are a vector, okay? So when you… when you start to use, like, all the library, right, they call… so they can call this a vector.
germayne: You can call this a matrix.
germayne: You can call this a tensor.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: It's all the same terms, the same thing, it's just a number, and it's just a 1 by D dimension.
germayne: And then your D can be very big. So let's say in that example we saw it's 768, I think, and then 124. Usually, lah, usually they fix… they go 2 to the power or something, yeah.
germayne: Understand?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Hmm.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay? Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
Zac Ang: Sorry, do we need to know.
germayne: Hey, Sean.
Zac Ang: they get the coordinates when we talk about embedding. Because previous… so far, we've seen how we get the vectors.
germayne: -Oh.
Zac Ang: by counting the frequency. But the embedding, we haven't really seen how we get the numbers, convert the text to the…
germayne: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. So, I think we will talk a bit about it on Thursday for the attention.
germayne: Follow up.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because I think embedding is a… is like, you know,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: It seems like a new thing, you know, then it's like, yeah, yeah, so… Although it might not be, like, but to me, it seems like, yeah, I remember I heard this word before, but when it comes to here, it's like, how come, like, what's the importance now?
germayne: So basically, I think what I'm just trying to tell you is that if you train a neural network model, you are able to encode some kind of representation, you can call it the embedding. And that is not… that is not strictly applied only to text data or image data. If you train a feed-forward neural network.
germayne: this example.
germayne: this… this N by D, this representation… sorry, this representation here, this one.
germayne: These are what are… what we call the embeddings.
germayne: of… Your flat type.
germayne: Because I'm able to represent these 6 by D flat type in a vector space. Agreed? They are all in D dimension. So by right, right, by right, by right, and there are papers for this. By right, if your model trains is trained correctly, I do a PCA and I plot them, right, for example.
germayne: what's your expectation? You guys should expect all the HDB flats to be close together, correct? And then maybe you're landed and your condo is far away.
germayne: That should be the expectation.
germayne: From the data, because I would imagine resale prices should be closely together while your lender is actually away. Is that… there's lender data, right?
germayne: In your resio? No?
germayne: Don't have, is it? Okay.
germayne: So maybe your HDB and your… maybe some of the jumbo flag or whatever lah. So what is learning is that because you are training the model using gradient descent.
germayne: and it's updating using, let's say, again, depends on what you're training. If you're training on the resale flat, then I should expect
germayne: houses that have similar resale flats to be close together. That's what the embedding is learning, 6 by D, D dimension.
germayne: So, embedding is not strictly restricted to NLP or image data, alright?
germayne: there's a.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I remember it can be on any… anything, you know, like…
germayne: No, no, it's not on anything. Usually, it's an output from a neural network.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: And historically, in the past, there's this layer called the embedding layer, which is this. It's just a lookup. It's just a lookup table. But this lookup table gets updated during gradient descent as well, because you initialize them randomly as well.
germayne: And it gets updated. So it's able to represent any kind of data into D-dimension space, and people usually like to use it for categorical variable.
germayne: Because if you think about it, right, this is actually very similar to me doing one-hot encoding or whatever, right? I'm representing.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, yeah, correct, correct.
germayne: Correct? If you do 100 encoding, this becomes… N by whatever number of Variable that you have, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: So, I can actually represent this. So, actually, I can have many embedding layers, one for each categorical variable.
germayne: And it should naturally learn the representation.
germayne: Alright.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, I think I… okay.
germayne: Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: It's just not…
germayne: lah, I think it's just… it's just getting used to it. I think if you… if you are in this space for quite a while, you… you… you get exposed to this, and, you know, you build all of this.
germayne: you will familiarize yourself. So I think if it's the first time, then I think there's quite a lot of terms. Yeah, and then, and…
germayne: Again, my advice is to learn the embedding layer, it's best you go and implement it yourself. Then you will know how it works.
germayne: Alright?
germayne: It's just a one line… okay, by the way, it's not very complex, it's just a one line, it's just an embedding layer. If you use PyTorch, it's just one line, just one line of code. It's actually very, very easy, yeah.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Got it?
germayne: Okay, I think, I think soon's, last part, right, let's continue tomorrow. Anyways, we are going to talk about neural network.
germayne: For… for… for the last… last lesson.
germayne: I would suggest… I would say, right, the last one is actually the hardest.
germayne: Because we are going into, like, the harder part of neural network already.
germayne: Okay, so if, let's say, you guys feel that the last… the last lesson… so if you guys feel like today is difficult, it will be an expansion of what we talked about today, the last part.
germayne: Like, all of these, I think I talked a bit about the attention, the attention, this, this one.
germayne: We talk about attention, but I… but we will provide the materials for you guys to go through, like, the materials that, if you take your time, you can take your time to understand it, but it's a bit mathematical.
germayne: Okay? If you really want to understand. If you don't want to understand, I think it's optional, it's fine. Just need to know what is the difference.
germayne: between attention and the older algorithms, the LSTM and RNN.
germayne: Okay, so it's called optional. The last one, obviously, is called the Advanced NLP, right?
germayne: Is it important to know the math? I think it depends. If you are a user of the large language model, then maybe you don't want to know. But if you want to know how it works, then good to know.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay.
germayne: Okay, so I'll leave the last part to be completely optional.
germayne: In terms of, like, the math.
germayne: Okay? But I think it will be a bit complex on Thursday. And if you struggle to understand, just…
germayne: Be… be assured to know that it is a tough concept.
germayne: It's, like, at the pinnacle, it's really at the pinnacle. I mean, if you really understand, then you understand how large language model works to some extent, to some extent.
germayne: Okay? Because the field is changing very, very fast, they're always introducing new stuff.
germayne: So, obviously, whatever I cover on Thursday will have not… will not be exactly the same as, oh, DeepSig V4, it will not be, right? Because DeepSig V4 just has its own paper. You have to read the paper again, from scratch.
germayne: But the foundation is built on all of this.
germayne: Okay? So if you're comfortable, you want to challenge yourself, then the Thursday's lessons will be relevant. If not, then I think you can always revisit if you need it.
germayne: Okay, got it, huh?
germayne: like a buffet, I think. I think that's the… that's the… that's the analogy, right? It's like a buffet.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, I think, I think that's all, I think we can close today.
germayne: We'll continue soon's notebook on Thursday, on the application of the embedding.
germayne: Okay, I think while I set up the… I set up the… the… the… IZ ticket.
germayne: You guys got any questions, can just ask me.
germayne: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, we're doing the survey, correct. Maybe, sorry, sorry, sorry, I think you guys are asking about different surveys, is it?
germayne: Is it the… the… Kendra, is it you asking about the… what do you call it? 30-question survey, is it?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Yeah, yeah.
germayne: Oh, that one, I don't have it. Why are you guys so anxious about that? I think we got time.
germayne: Oh.
germayne: Oh, no, the, the, the, the exit, the exit, oh, sorry, sorry, I used the word exit, right? Okay, okay, okay, sorry, sorry, we do the Slido. That, that one, I think, that one, I think not today, yeah, yeah, yeah.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, let me share my screen. Oh.
germayne: Okay, so I think this is the second-last lesson.
germayne: So, we are reaching the end.
germayne: Oh yeah, I will upload the slides now.
germayne: Forgot to add…
germayne: Okay, actually, we didn't talk a lot about attention, I'm so sorry if that became the important point. Attention is just really at the… it's actually for Thursday. The takeaway should be…
germayne: Yeah, it's just about the converting to vector, and you should take away with TF-IDF. I want to reiterate, TF-IDF is still very important. If you want to understand PM25, you need to understand TF-IDF anyways.
germayne: And… Is it relevant for RAG and Chanking? Definitely.
germayne: Okay? So it's not… it's not that it's without lexical semantics just words. You guys already know that it will not work for a lot of cases.
germayne: What's NLO?
germayne: Wow.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: High probability is a typo.
germayne: Oh…
germayne: Yeah, and I think the takeaway is that
germayne: If, let's say, you want to encode your text data, you have a lot of options to use pre-trained model, just like the same methodology for your
germayne: your text.
germayne: Right? You do… you wouldn't want to use a model from scratch. You can use a pre-trained model that people has trained, and you can easily just convert your data into embeddings, and that should be what you try… you should be trying.
germayne: Okay, so I'm sure you guys probably find the last part the most challenging, but I think the last part is really just the start of the next part.
germayne: So, mostly today's topic should be on TF-IDF.
germayne: call vectorizer.
germayne: engrams. That should be today's topic, okay? So whatever that we talk at the back, I think it's actually for Thursday. It's not for… it's not for… not really for today.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: So think about the topics about today, if, let's say, you find it challenging for today, yeah.
germayne: Yeah, so, embedding is a concept that we'll explore more on Thursday.
germayne: But I'll just give you guys a heads up, it will be…
germayne: I would say it's one of the more challenging Topic.
germayne: Within the whole deep learning space.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I guess that because there are many terms, so…
germayne: It's a need.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: to…
germayne: -
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You know, it's the same terms mean the… the different terms mean the same thing, then it's like, okay, probably need to know about that, in case you don't get… you get hang out and say, oh, you know, it's a new… it's this, and another one, then another one.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Same, right? That is probably good to know that it's the same.
germayne: So, it's the context, right? So, I think very similar to what we see here, I think it's the context.
germayne: So if you use embedding in certain contexts, it's correct, and people will know what you're saying, because that's how people use it. Yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, yeah.
germayne: But people don't… don't call it embedding for TF IDF, for example.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, yeah, correct. That's what I meant also, because it's like, otherwise, like, oh, you're like, oh, another one there, another one there, like… so if I need to build a model, I need to know what this and this and this, but Azure Fight is the same thing, all that, oh, you know?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, that's where I… that's where I come in from,
germayne: I think door is better.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: My understanding was, and Benny was that it's supposed to add something so that it's, you know, it makes your…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Searching, or what retrieval, easier, man.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: For one round.
germayne: Yes, yes, yes, but that is in the context of converting your unstructured data to a vector space, correct?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, yeah, something like that, like, so that it's… yeah, that's what I remember. Because what I read is, like, it's that way, but I'm not sure, like, very correctly, but, you know, like.
germayne: Correct, correct, it's correct. I think… I think on Saturday, when we do the summary, what I want is that, as a class participation, you guys will just tell me all the topics, then we'll just summarize in the overall mind map.
germayne: Okay, hopefully that will help in consolidating all the topics.
germayne: Okay, so 50-50, 50 people say it's very fast. Oh, today is actually very fast, serious? For the TF idea?
germayne: -Oh.
germayne: those that put fast maybe can give a comment. Is it on the TF idea, or what? Or is it the last part? The last part is on Thursday, though. It's not really today. I think we just talked about it.
germayne: Yeah, but the embedding is not the goal of today.
germayne: Yeah?
germayne: the embedding is not the goal of today. Today, the takeaway should be, I know how to do TF-IDF. I think that should be the takeaway.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, but I'm giving you guys a heads up on Thursday. I think Thursday will be about… we'll go deeper about that.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so what do you think is a good takeaway today? That was… I hope that actually this supplements what CP thought on Saturday, I think.
germayne: Should be clearer, right?
germayne: Right? So you guys now have an… have a… should be… should be able to visualize
germayne: Why is it that you need to…
germayne: Convert the chunks into vector space.
germayne: And when we do a retrieval from a query, how do you know which chunks are similar? I think today you guys should actually have that… that… that… that linkage today. Yeah, exactly.
germayne: It's based on…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I got… I got a question, though, because there are so many new technologies coming out.
germayne: Subway.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: There was somewhere we… in the beginning today, we learned about tokenization and everything, so…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: those are, like, basic, yeah, but… Yeah. But is this something that I need to do now? Because so many, if I use… let's say I use my pre-trained model, I don't have to worry about all this anymore, right?
germayne: Okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, I'm thinking, like, from the…
germayne: Yes and no, no problem.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, it's the same point of view.
germayne: Yeah, so… so to answer your question, right, if you were to… if you want to explore large language models, you realize that there's this concept of tokenizer.
germayne: But then if today you never learned Tokenizer, then you will know what it is, what?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: God.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: So if, let's say, you play with large language model, you'll know that there's this tokenizing concept. When I say play with, it's not like, go and use it, you know? Basically, load the model, and then see how does it… you will see that there's this tokenizer, but then, if you never heard of tokenizer, then you'll be like, okay, what's tokenizer?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay. So, so knowing it, and then, and then doing, and then, do, doing… doing it.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: It's a different thing, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I'm like.
germayne: So why not, Noel, I ask you, when you learn about all the models, and then you do your Kaggle, is it different, or is it the same?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I will do all the thing again, or I will do all the pre…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: the feature, the data engineering, and all that kind of stuff, or the EDA, and all that kind of stuff.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, I'm assuming I do… I need to do, lah.
germayne: Of course.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, yeah.
germayne: Oh, yeah, you need to do everything, yes. So you need to know anything you need to do, yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, okay, Ken, ken, Ken, thank you, thank you.
germayne: Okay, yeah, so today you guys learned the basics, and…
germayne: I will still say it's important. It is still important, yeah?
germayne: Okay, so… what… What will be the part that you guys want to improve on, based on today's class?
germayne: Rewatch the video.
germayne: Yeah, I would suggest for today, just make sure you understand TF-IDF.
germayne: And convectorizo.
germayne: From a conceptual standpoint.
germayne: Yeah?
germayne: a transformer get ready for Thursday's class. Okay, if to be honest, if you can read up and understood, right.
germayne: then I would say Thursday, you… you… it wouldn't be difficult, because
germayne: there's no way you… I mean, it would be very hard if, let's say, you were to just listen to what I say and just understand. So, I think this is a good suggestion. If, let's say, you're super interested in it.
germayne: you can just do some pre-reading, try to see if you can get any material. I think there's a lot on the web.
germayne: Because, I mean, it's the latest thing, everybody… I mean, not latest, I'm just telling you, it's been, like, many years already, but…
germayne: is the best right now, so I'm sure there'll be a lot of material. So, I would suggest if, let's say, you're super interested, then you guys can look into it. If not, then just wait for the class, yeah?
germayne: Not a prerequisite, lah, yeah, not a prerequisite.
germayne: Okay, okay, I'll wait for the last person. Okay, if, if you guys have no questions, then…
germayne: do stay back if you have any questions on setting up and stuff. If not, then thank you so much for the evening.
germayne: I'll see you guys for the last class on Thursday. Last weekday class with me. Not the last… not the last… you guys still have, like, other modules, so not the last for yourself, but the last with me.
germayne: Right? For weekday, okay?
germayne: Yeah, thank you so much, and have a good evening, yeah.
Zac Ang: Thank you.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Dude.
germayne: See you guys on Thursday. Yeah, yeah. Bye-bye.
Josiah Ho: You…
germayne: Thank you, thank you. Yeah, thanks, Brian.
Soon | NTU: Bye.
germayne: And thanks, Alvin.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Fight.
Edwin Yap: I mean, just curious, what's not what you said, if you get ready for Thursday class, what do I need to prepare?
germayne: No, nothing, nothing. I mean, you don't have to prepare anything.
Edwin Yap: Okay, bye.
germayne: Yeah, it's okay.
germayne: It's okay if you… it's okay to come in, yeah? I don't think it's meant to… it's a prerequisite to be anything. If… if you just want to really solid… solidify the understanding, yeah, of course you can read up on Transformers, but…
germayne: I… I wouldn't say it's, like, a required prerequisite lah, I think, yeah. Alright?
Edwin Yap: Okay. One last question. So, just now, when we were doing the word embedding, right, so weren't the content or the intent lost.
germayne: Word embedding, the intent laws, what do you mean?
Edwin Yap: No, because I remember, you know, when I was looking at the breaking up of the words for embedding, right?
germayne: Sorry, what do you mean?
Edwin Yap: when I was looking at the model, so I was thinking, how does the model able to understand the meaning when they have picked up the words? Because it won't know the intent of the words, right?
germayne: When they break up the words.
Edwin Yap: Right.
germayne: Ocho example.
Edwin Yap: Yeah, I think when I saw the.
germayne: Hey, Se.
Edwin Yap: Different weightage to the words, yeah.
germayne: Oh, this one.
germayne: This one, this one, this one.
Edwin Yap: Yes, yeah, I am a boy, something like that.
germayne: Okay, so what was the question?
Edwin Yap: The question is that if they… they just… they will read only one, I, former, M, former, former boy. Yeah. They break up.
Edwin Yap: But they won't know the intent of the word, right?
germayne: No, the attention will compute the attention with respect to each word.
germayne: So here you calculate one time, here you calculate two times, Here, you calculate 3 times.
germayne: And then here you calculate 4 times.
Edwin Yap: Okay.
germayne: You can see, right?
Edwin Yap: one.
Edwin Yap: Your attention.
germayne: So the, the, the attention actually do look at the context. So it's not… it's not, it's not looking at eye independently.
germayne: is looking at whole thing as a whole. That's why…
germayne: depending on who is in the context, the embeddings would change. Which makes sense, right? Which means that, actually, it does understand the difference between I'm a boy, I'm a girl.
Edwin Yap: Hmm.
germayne: Right?
germayne: Correct.
Edwin Yap: Yep.
germayne: Yeah, so that's the intuition.
Edwin Yap: So this will be covered on Thursday, lah.
germayne: Yes, we'll talk about this again on Thursday. There are two ways to understand this, either from a hand-wavy perspective, analogy, or from the math standpoint.
Edwin Yap: The meth… yeah, I find.
germayne: The math is good, the math is hard, yes.
Edwin Yap: I lost track… I lost…
germayne: But I think it's okay lah, I mean, you don't need the math.
germayne: For this, you're not doing it on a day-to-day basis, you don't need to know the math.
Edwin Yap: You're right, yes.
germayne: I think having an idea, I think, is good enough. Having an idea on… I will talk about the Thursday analogy, don't worry. I'll give a… I'll give a simple analogy, yeah. Just understand from the analogy, you don't have to understand the math.
Edwin Yap: Okay.
Edwin Yap: Everyone have an early morning tomorrow, so thank you.
germayne: Thank you so much, yep, thank you so much.
Edwin Yap: Thanks, no.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): zombies for Transformers, right?
germayne: Yep.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): for Transformers?
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): the IMO boy. The boy will link to IME.
germayne: Yes, yes, exactly.
germayne: It looks at the whole context, that's why it's called attention. It attends to every context in the sentence.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Okay, so this will go through more hotels here.
germayne: Yes, we'll talk more about it on Thursday, don't worry.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Okay, thank you so much.
germayne: Thank you so much.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): But they were asking Arnemo to connect with me on…
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): LinkedIn, yeah, I think you didn't…
germayne: Oh, okay, but you can use Discord, mah, remember? We said that, we talked about that, right? You can use Discord.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Yo, yo, yo.
germayne: Yeah, so don't worry, don't worry, Tomac, yeah.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Okay, okay, just connect to me on LinkedIn.
germayne: Okay, okay, yep, bye-bye.
Daniel Chan Chee Seng (Chen Zhisheng): Boy.